[ Music ]
[ Applause ]
>> Good afternoon.
Welcome to WC 2016.
Quite a bit has happened
since we met about a year ago.
With the addition of tvOS, then
our four Apple OS platforms,
a lot of them with
their own app store,
and all our platforms
are optimized
for their own unique
experiences.
But they share a tremendous
amount of common technologies
and APIs, making it easy
for you to bring your apps
to all four platforms
by leveraging the individual
character at the same time.
Our expert tool chain is the
same for all four platforms.
They share most of their
frameworks and libraries,
and the underlying
programming concepts
and programming languages
are the same as well.
And today we are announcing a
ton of new APIs and technologies
that you'll be able
to take advantage of.
You'll find many more ways
to express your ideas,
and you'll be able to
target even more users
in even more markets.
Our iOS X in particular is
huge this year for developers.
In fact, if you take a
look at the iOS at least
that we announced this morning,
you'll find that we are opening
up pretty much the entire user
experience of iOS to developers,
covering everything from
notifications to Phone,
Messages, Maps, and even Siri.
An important concept that we use
to achieve that is extensions,
and you might remember that
we introduced extensions two
years ago.
They represent an increasingly
important mechanism for us
because they allow you to
branch out from your apps
and to participate in
our system functionality.
They allow you to
securely customize our OS's
by running short-lived
sandboxed services
that are launched on demand.
Our shipping products already
support a broad variety
of extension points, and we're
adding many more this year,
allowing you to hook even
deeper into our OS's and apps.
Perhaps the most exciting
new extension point is
for creating iMessage Apps.
And to tell you all about it,
I'm going to hand
over to Darin Adler.
[ Applause ]
>> So I'm having a great
time with the new Messages,
and I hope you all will too.
iMessage Apps are how you
can be a part of that.
Now, as Andreas mentioned,
iMessage Apps are extensions,
and that means that like other
extensions, you can include them
in your apps on the App Store.
But with iMessage Apps,
there's another option as well.
You can include them in
the iMessage App Store,
which you get at right
from inside Messages.
Looks like this.
Now, when you send interactive
messages with your iMessage App,
you'll have the icon of
the app up in the corner,
but even more importantly,
if the person you send
that interactive message to
doesn't have the app yet,
they'll have this link that
says, "Get a name of app."
If you tap on that link.
That takes you right to
getting or buying the app,
so it's an amazing way to have
your customers spread your app
from one person to another.
Now, if you're building
a Sticker Pack App,
it's really simple.
There's no coding required.
You just take all of the
graphics for the icons
for the app, the
graphics for the stickers,
put them into Xcode, build, and
then submit to iTunes Connect.
If you want to make a
more sophisticated app
and take advantage of all
the power in iMessage Apps,
you program with Swift
and use UIKit just
like with other extensions.
And there's a new
Messages extension point.
The classes in this Messages
extension point give you access
to everything you need
inside the Messages App.
So there's an object
representing a message
that you send.
There's an object representing
the whole conversation the
message is part of.
There's even an object
representing a thing called a
session, which lets you
group messages together,
and it's a really great way to
do collaborative iMessage Apps.
Now, all of this is done
without compromising the privacy
that Messages is famous for.
Your app doesn't have
any access to anything
in the conversation outside of
what's being done with the app,
and if, it doesn't even
necessarily know who's involved,
who you're sending to, so that
helps keep the privacy intact.
Now, adaptive design
is important
to any iOS app development,
and it's even more
important for iMessage Apps.
That's because Messages runs in
all the different kinds of sizes
and shapes of devices
and all the adaptations.
And so it runs on iPad, it runs
on iPhone, it runs in slide
over an iPad, portrait
and landscape,
and so your iMessage
Apps need to too.
But there's one additional
wrinkle for iMessage Apps,
which is that they run in this
Compact Mode down at the bottom
of the screen where the
keyboard is and you can slide
between them or you
can take that same app
and expand it to its full size.
Sometimes the app will do it.
Sometimes the user will do it.
Adaptive design is
very important
to that experience as well.
Everything you need to develop
iMessage Apps is available,
and so you can really start now.
The SDK has all the things
I talked about everything
from the Messages
extension point.
And the simulator even
has a new, special version
of Messages just for developers
that lets you see both sides
of a conversation and try
out your iMessage Apps
to see how they're
both sent and received.
And now Adele Peterson
will show you how all
of this comes together in iOS X.
[ Applause ]
>> Thanks, Darin.
As you saw this morning,
our friends at Disney have
made some awesome stickers,
so I'm going to show
you how they did it
by putting together a
sticker app in Xcode.
Now, this only takes a minute,
so even though I'm
starting a new project,
I'm actually almost done.
I'm going to start by
selecting the Sticker Pack
application template.
I'll give it a good name
like Star Wars, save it,
and I'll select the
Stickers Asset Catalog.
Now, I want my stickers to have
a great icon when I look at them
in the Messages app
drawer, so I'll start
by dragging in my icons.
And now I can select my sticker
pack and drag my stickers in.
Okay, let's give that a try.
Now that Messages is in the
simulator, it will be easy
for you to try out your
stickers in iMessage Apps.
Okay, so let's launch
the sticker pack.
I just love this 8-bit droid.
So I can test out sending one
and I can even test out peeling
and dragging a sticker
onto another message.
Looks great.
And that's how easy it
is to make a sticker app.
[ Applause ]
Now onto iMessage Apps.
So I've got this ice cream app
here, and my daughter's really
into these kinds of
apps that let her design
and create things, so I'm
making an iMessage App for her
to build ice cream
stickers with her friends.
So here in the Compact View,
you have the completed
ice cream stickers,
and when I tap the
plus, the app expands
and shows the ice
cream building UI.
So I'm going to select a
cone here and start this off.
So I'm going to select
it and send.
So now the simulator shows both
the sender and receiver sides
of the conversation,
so you don't even need
to use two iOS devices to
test your iMessage App.
In this view, I'm
actually John Appleseed
and I'm sending the
cone to Kate Bell.
Let's look at it from the
other side of the conversation.
So here Kate's received
the cone.
You can tap on the message,
launch the app, add some scoops,
and send it back to John.
And then on the other side
of the conversation,
you receive this.
You tap the message,
you add a topping,
and send it back to Kate.
Now, as delicious
as this all looks,
I don't really want my entire
conversation to be filled
with these partially
built ice cream cones.
There's actually a much
cleaner way to build this kind
of collaborative iMessage App.
If I use the same MS session
for each of those messages,
then the earlier steps
of building ice cream
will be replaced
by concise descriptions, and
you'll only see the later,
the latest ice cream message.
So I'm going to make
that change in Xcode
and show you how it looks.
So let me switch over to
the ice cream project.
Let's see.
Okay, so here's the
part of my code
that creates the
MS message object.
I'm going to drag in -- oops --
I'm going to drag in this code.
This code looks to see
if there's a selected
message in the conversation.
That's what you get when
you tap that message
and it launches the
app full screen.
So if there is a
selected message,
we'll use the session
associated with that message,
and if there isn't, we'll
pass in a fresh MS session.
So let's give that a try.
Okay, so now we'll
launch this app again.
We'll tap the Plus button,
select a cone, send it to Kate,
add some toppings, send it back
to John, and then finish it off,
and send it back to Kate.
So now you can see those
descriptions describing the
earlier steps of the process,
and you no longer have those
partially built ice creams
sitting on top of
the finished product.
And that is a little taste
of what you can do
with iMessage Apps.
Next up, Robby Walker
to tell you about Siri.
[ Applause ]
>> Thank you, Adele.
Five years ago, we
announced Siri,
the intelligent assistant
for iPhone.
Since then, Siri has spoken
to people hundreds
of billions of times.
As of today, Siri is now
available on five classes
of devices and in a
whopping 36 locales.
Siri also has many new features
and an improved core experience.
One cool example, on
iPhone 6s and 6s Plus,
you can start talking to Siri
the instant you press the Home
button with literally zero
milliseconds of latency thanks
to an amazing collaboration
between our hardware
and software teams.
But of course, until today,
something really important has
been missing, and that's apps,
so we're so excited to
launch the first version
of SiriKit on iOS.
[ Applause ]
We believe the best
experience for people is
to use the apps they love,
the apps you all have created,
and with SiriKit, people
will now be able to interact
with those applications in
a new, conversational way.
I'm going to talk about how
your application will work
with SiriKit to provide a great,
conversational experience.
The first thing Siri does is
understand what the user said,
taking audio and
turning it into text.
Then, Siri understands what the
user means, taking that text
and turning it into
what we call an intent.
Based off that, on that
intent, Siri then takes action
and provides responses,
both visual and verbal.
Your application will
provide three things.
The first is vocabulary to
aid in Siri's understanding.
The second is your app logic,
your core functionality,
and of course, a
great user interface.
Now, we designed SiriKit so that
Siri handles the conversation
and your application
handles the functionality.
And what's great about that is
it means it's incredibly easy
to adopt SiriKit and your
users can expect a consistent,
high-quality experience
that's natural,
feels like a conversation
and not like a command line.
Let's dig in a bit.
The first role of
your application is
to provide vocabulary,
and there's two kinds.
The first is app vocabulary.
These are terms that
would be known
to any user of your application.
Things like UberX or Pinboard.
The other is user vocabulary.
These are terms that are
specific and important
to an individual user
of your application.
Things like their contact
names or names of photo albums.
The main role of
your application is
to provide your app
logic, and this comes
in an extension at
three key moments.
The first is to help Siri
understand the parameters
of the user's intent.
The second is to help Siri show
the user what will happen if
and when they confirm
their intent.
And the third is to actually
of course handle the intent,
to accomplish what the
user came to accomplish.
And during the conversation,
Siri presents visuals
to the user, and you can
optionally provide a second
extension to customize
these so that using Siri
with your application
still feels
like using your application
anywhere else.
So let's take a look
at a messaging app
integration called Hologram.
Hologram is the number one
app for sending messages
in a galaxy far, far away.
So imagine someone says
to Siri, "Send a hologram
to Obi-Wan saying,
you're my only hope."
Now, it's Siri's job to
take that audio and turn it
into text, but Siri needs
help from your application.
Siri doesn't know on its own
that Obi-Wan is an important
user or important person
in your user's life, and
so by providing that piece
of vocabulary to
Siri, you make sure
that Siri understands
what your user said.
Next, Siri works to understand
what the user is trying to do.
In this case, send a
very important message.
And Siri will also work
to understand parameters,
like the recipient
and the content.
Siri packages all
of this information
into a structured object
a nice, simple object.
Your application
doesn't have to worry
about the countless ways someone
could express this same idea
to Siri, whether it be
different phrasings,
multi-step interactions.
All of that's handled
and all you have to worry
about is this really
simple object.
SiriKit will then hand this
object to your extension to help
with parameter resolution.
For example, maybe
your application knows
that the user said "Obi-Wan,"
but they usually refer
to this person as
Old Ben Kenobi,
and you can instruct
SiriKit to update the intent.
Then comes the big event.
It's time to actually
handle the user's intent,
and SiriKit will
again hand this object
to your extension
for processing.
In this case, you're going to
send the message, you're going
to get in an escape pod,
roll over some sand dunes,
deal with some Jawas.
You're going to get the
job done for your users.
And along the way, Siri will
provide a default user interface
for this interaction.
And if you want, you can
also bring your application's
experience into Siri so
that it feels more familiar
to your users.
And that's it.
Those are the three things
that your application has to do
because SiriKit handles
the conversation.
And handling the conversation
actually means a lot.
Siri's behavior is
different depending
on how someone starts a
conversation with Siri.
So if you're holding your
phone, pressing the Home button,
looking at your screen,
Siri will provide
more visual responses
and say less things out loud.
But if you say, "Hey,
Siri," or if you're
in the car using
CarPlay, then Siri's going
to show a lot more
and, or sorry,
say a lot more and
show a lot less.
SiriKit is powered by
extensions and NSUserActivity,
the same technologies that
power an increasing number
of OS integrations, and you'll
hear a lot about them this week.
This year, SiriKit will connect
to applications in six domains,
and in each of these
domains, there may be more
than one intent to
provide a complete,
conversational experience.
For example, in Messaging,
you can send messages
or search them, and in Payments,
you can request payment
or send payment.
And SiriKit will be available
in all Siri languages,
and this is a big deal
because when I said earlier
that Siri handles
the conversation,
what I actually mean is Siri
handles the conversation
in all 36 locales so that
your application doesn't have
to worry about that.
[ Applause ]
We're so excited to
see what you'll build
and so is someone else we know.
Siri, say hello to apps.
>> I'm swiftly becoming
friends with them.
>> And on that note,
here is Chris Lattner
to talk about Swift.
[ Applause ]
>> All right.
Thanks, Robby.
Let's dive in to
what's new with Swift?
Now, it's easy to forget
that we launched Swift
and released it less
than two years ago,
and in that short time,
you've built and submitted
to the App Store
over 100,000 apps,
including well-known
titles like these.
Now, Swift has also
been very popular
with the enterprise as well.
Just as a simple example,
IBM's already built
and deployed hundreds of
apps written in Swift.
Now--
[ Applause ]
Now, there's lots of reasons
that people love Swift,
one of which is that
we open sourced it less
than six months ago.
[ Applause ]
And in that time, it's become
the number one most downloaded
language project on GitHub,
the number one most watched,
and the number one
most favorited,
and it's stayed on top.
I think to me, even better than
this is that we've had a ton
of new people get
involved with the project.
We now have hundreds of new
contributors contributing
through open source, and
we've processed thousands
of poll requests.
The response has
just been phenomenal.
Now, one of the reasons
that Swift being open is really
important to us is that we want
to see it go everywhere.
For example, we think that
Swift is awesome for the server,
and so we ported it to Linux.
And the community agrees.
In a very short period of time,
they've started bringing it
to other popular
platforms like FreeBSD,
Android, and even Windows.
[ Applause ]
Now, to help Swift get to
all of these platforms,
we started the Swift
Package Manager.
The Package Manager's a
great way to build, share,
and reuse cross-platform
packages.
It can generate an
Xcode project file
and even compile
projects natively
on platforms like Linux.
Another great thing about Swift
Open Source is you can get
involved with the design
of the language itself.
Swift-evolution has been
an amazing experience
with intense interest in
a completely insane number
of emails on mailing lists.
It's ridiculous.
Now, we published an open
roadmap with the goals
for each release,
and we solicit ideas
and discuss different
directions we could go
to push the language
forward together.
We then debate these
together openly as a community
and we turn them into
formal proposals.
So far, we've had over 100
proposals to move Swift forward.
This is only in six months, and
this is just an amazing sign
of how fast Swift moves.
But it also shows another
important and interesting point.
Despite its wide use, Swift
is still a relatively new
programming language.
Now, as you've seen
I think, we've chosen
to quickly identify issues in
the Swift language and fix them
because we don't want to be
stuck with issues forever.
We are building Swift as the
next great programming language,
and so we want it to be great
for the decades to come.
And now the problem with this
is that for some developers,
the programming language
changing
out from underneath you can be
concerning, and as Swift goes
to new platforms and new kinds
of users with Swift Playgrounds,
this becomes an even
bigger concern.
So with that as context,
let's dive into what's
new with Swift 3.
Swift 3. We announced
it in December as part
of the open source
launch of Swift,
and we've been developing
it completely in the open.
The number one feature and the
number one goal of Swift 3 is
to get these early growing
pains over with and turn Swift
into a stable and mature base
that we can keep compatible
with future versions
of the language.
No?
[ Applause ]
So because of that, we're
focusing on the core essentials
of the language and
making the tools
and the development
experience really great.
And there are a ton
of different ways
that you can see this in Swift.
To give you a simple
example, one common complaint
about Swift 2 is that
the feel of some APIs
in Cocoa didn't feel
natural in Swift.
Swift loves clarity and it aims
to define away boilerplate.
On Swift 3, Cocoa APIs
have an elegant feel.
You could say they're
totally Swifty.
Now, we did this with a number
of different initiatives.
First, we sat down
and thought hard
about what really makes a great
Swift API, and we wrote it
down in a document that's
now available on Swift.org.
We then took that and took
those rules and built them right
into the Swift recompiler, so
it automatically applies them
to Objective-C APIs as it
imports them into Swift.
But Swift goes far
beyond just naming.
Naming's a pretty
hard problem, though,
but it goes beyond just naming.
And if you look at
foundation as a simple example,
you'll find entirely new
Swift native data types.
Date is an example of this, and
if you compare Date to NSDate,
you'll find that it provides
proper value semantics,
it's about twice as
fast to pass around,
and it's about 40 times
faster to change due
to reduced MalCon
[phonetic] free traffic.
[ Applause ]
Now, there are examples
everywhere,
and as Calendar becomes
Calendar,
Global Constants become
scoped enums, Date Components,
NSDate Components becomes
a proper value type,
and everything is
just feeling so Swift.
If you move beyond foundation,
Dispatch is another critical API
that we work with
all of the time,
but it provides this
low-level, C-style interface.
With Swift 3, Dispatch has
gotten a major overhaul,
has a beautiful object-oriented
API.
[ Applause ]
And it follows all the best
naming practices that you expect
from a great Swift API.
Core graphics is
another example of that.
Here's some typical core
graphics code, and in Swift 3,
it's elegant, beautiful, and
it works just like you expect.
[ Applause ]
Now, Swift 3 has a
ton of great features
that you can learn
about all week long.
Swift 3 is available in Xcode 8,
and Xcode provides a
fantastic migration assistant
to help move your code from
Swift 2 to Swift 3 syntax.
Even better, Xcode 8
also includes Swift 2.3,
which means that you can
move to Swift 3 syntax
when the time is right for you.
[ Applause ]
So that's all I have
for you today.
Thank you, and I'll hand
it back to Andreas to talk
about the next big
thing, Swift on the iPad.
[ Applause ]
>> Thank you, Chris.
So another aspect of Swift
that excites us is that it's
so simple and so approachable
that it's not just great
for implementing apps
and server components.
It's also great as a first
program language to learn.
In fact, we think this
is super important,
and when we designed Swift,
that's also an explicit
goal we had.
And right from the
launch of Swift,
we introduced Xcode Playgrounds,
an interactive environment
where you can quickly
iterate on your code.
And while it's great
for experienced developers
using our Xcode IDE,
and I want to dramatically
expand our focus
and include kits for just
beginning to learn how to code.
So today we are announcing
Swift Playgrounds,
a new app for the iPad.
You've already seen a demo
this morning with the keynote.
It is paired with Xcode
technology, but it's made
from the ground up for learning
and teaching how
to program Swift.
It's both playful and engaging
for the younger audience,
and it's a fun way of
trying out new things
for experienced developers.
It is designed to work with the
touch interface of the iPad.
We created a new Smart Keyboard
that brings you quick type
suggestions for your code,
similar to code completion
in Xcode.
You often can write entire
lines of code without having
to bring up a full keyboard.
When you edit inline values
such as numbers and colors,
we pop up these quick editing
controls that allow you
to easily select a value,
again, without having
to bring up a full keyboard.
You can quickly change the
code in your Playground simply
by dragging the structural
elements
on the screen with your finger.
And as you would
expect, there's a library
of prebuilt code snippets you
can insert into your code simply
with a tap or again by
dragging them with your finger.
And for the times where you
do bring up a full keyboard
to write some code,
we present you
with a dedicated
coding keyboard,
which makes it super easy
to access the many special
characters and numbers
that you need for
writing Swift code.
Just with a swipe of a finger.
No need to switch
keyboard planes.
The app also ships the
fantastic lesson content.
We're building an
entire series of lessons
that will introduce you to
programming Swift step by step
and we're planning to
rapidly expand this content
over the course of the
next year, but you can go
in to provide learners
with a steam of challenges
that they're going
to update frequently.
So they keep coming back
to the app and stay engaged
with the learning process for
the number of deep dive topics.
But you're not limited
to following this
guided lesson content.
You also have the power and the
flexibility to explore coding
on your own with a set
of simple templates.
We created one that makes it
easy to put together a program
with just text input and output
and another one that allows you
to explore and visualize
graphics concepts based
on shapes.
And beyond that, since you
have the entire iOS SDK
at your fingertips, you're free
to create pretty much
any Playground you'd like
and use the app to
teach many topics.
You can even control robots
like this one here on the screen
and other accessories
from your Playground,
so it ends up being
a lot of fun.
And to just show you
a little bit more
about how you can leverage the
app, I'm going to ask Ken Orr
to give us another demo.
[ Applause ]
>> Right. Thanks, Andreas.
Swift Playgrounds makes it easy
to get creative through code,
so let's take a look
at a Playground
that I created earlier and
I'll show you just what I mean.
Now, I started here with
the Shapes template,
and you can see the
beginnings of my picture
over there on the right.
So just some squares
of different sizes
and colors rotated
around the center.
Now, everything over on
the right is a product
of my code on the left.
At the heart of my code
over here is this for loop.
That's where I create
each one of those squares.
And then up at the very
top, I've got a variable
that defines how many
squares I should create.
Well, right now, that's set to
15, but I'd really like to get
that entire right-hand side
to be filled up with color,
so to do that, let me just
try bumping this up to 80,
and then I'll tap Run.
Nice. And I think maybe instead
of maroon, I'll use a nice blue.
That looks good.
And I really like the pattern
that I've got going on here
where the squares,
they're kind of spiraling
down into the center
of the Canvas.
That looks really cool.
I bet I could make
that even more obvious
if I change the size of those
squares more dramatically
over time.
So back down in the for loop
here where I calculate the size,
I'm going to tap on the plus
between these two
different expressions.
Rather than just
adding them together,
why don't I try multiplication?
Run that. That looks good.
So you can start to get an
idea of just how easy it is
to explore and experiment
with code using just a touch.
So next, I'd like to
bring a little bit
of life to my picture.
I'll use some animation
for that.
Now, to do that, I'm going
to use some API that's built
in to the Shapes template,
and I think what I want is I
want the squares to pop and spin
in from the center
of the stream.
So I'm going to tap right here
after I create each square,
and then down in the shortcuts
bar, I'm going to scroll over
and I'm going to tap on
the Animate function.
So I'll have an animation
that's maybe three seconds long
and I'll have it wait for just
one second before it starts,
and then everything that I put
inside of that block there.
It's going to be automatically
animated for me, so I'm going
to pull in the rotation
like that.
And then I also want the size
of the square to animate,
so I think I'll start it out
at zero width and zero height,
and then back in
the Animate block,
I'll set it to what
it was before.
So I'll say square.size
equals size,
and then I already calculated
the size above, so I'll just use
that same variable,
and I'll tap Run.
Very cool.
So it's starting
to come to life.
Thank you.
[ Applause ]
And there's one more thing
that I'd like to do here.
I'd like to add a little
bit of touch handling.
And to do that, I'm going to
use some more API that's built
into the Shapes template.
And down here at the bottom,
I've actually already added
a drag handler to the Canvas.
The block's waiting
for me to fill it in,
and I've also written
a function here
that will rotate each square
around the center of the Canvas.
So I just need to call that
function in this block here.
So back in the shortcuts bar,
I'm going to say
squares.rotateforTouches
and then I'll tap Run.
And now I'm going to
tap my finger and hold
in the top right, and
I'm going to pull down,
and just like that, I've
added Touch Handling.
Thank you.
[ Applause ]
By the way, you may have
noticed that so far,
I haven't actually needed the
full keyboard for any of this,
and I think that's pretty cool.
There's one more thing that I'd
like to show you this afternoon.
So I'm a UI guy.
I love building custom
controls and playful UI,
and I've been tinkering
around with this custom
color picker here.
I'd love to show you that.
So when you tap on the color
swatch, the Color Chooser pops
out from underneath your
finger and you can drag around
and pick the color you want.
Now, all the code to build
that is over on the left.
So let me make the code bigger
so we can take a quick look.
Now, the first thing you'll
notice, up at the very top,
I'm importing UIKit, so I
have access to the iOS SDK
in this Playground and in
any Playground that I create.
And then all the way
down at the bottom here,
this is where I tell Swift
Playgrounds to take my view
and show it over on
the right-hand side.
There's one last thing
that I'd like to add
to my Playground here, and
that's I want to add something
that I can set the color of so
that I can try out
my Color Chooser.
So I think to do that, I'll
just add a simple UI Image View,
so let me bring up the coding
keyboard, and I'm going to say,
"Let image view equal
UI Image View."
And I'm going to use the
initializer that takes an image,
and then I'm going to
tap on the third item
in the shortcut bar,
that little picture.
That's an image literal.
So when I tap on it in my
source code, I can choose
from resources that have been
added to this Playground.
[ Applause ]
So I added the Swift
bird earlier,
so I'm going to choose that.
And then last thing I need to
do here, I need to get you,
the UI Image View into
the view hierarchy,
so I'll just say
viewController.view.addSubview,
toss in the image view.
We'll run that, then I'm going
to make the view full screen.
And know we can see
I've got my image,
I've got our color picker,
and I actually snuck
in one little other
feature here.
I want it to be a little
bit more fun, set the color
of the bird, figured hey,
why not do it that way?
[ Applause ]
And that's Swift Playgrounds.
Thank you.
Andreas?
[ Applause ]
>> Thank you, Ken.
So as you saw, no matter what
kind of Playground you create,
you always do so by
leveraging the actual iOS SDK,
including the APIs that give you
access to the device's hardware.
And by writing real Swift code,
this is perhaps the
biggest differentiator
to other learning apps that
often use a limited approach
that users quickly outgrow.
In Swift Playgrounds,
you'll always learn how
to write real Swift code.
And by the way, as a side note,
the entire Playgrounds app
itself is also written in Swift.
[ Applause ]
So Swift Playgrounds offers
you many ways to experiment
and to teach and to learn how to
code, and we are very passionate
about letting as many users
as possible, especially kids,
take advantage of
this new opportunity.
And in fact, we hope that you
will help us create an entire
platform for learning by
creating additional content.
And to get you started, we're
going to make documentation
on our Playground's file format
available on our website today.
And later this year,
we are planning
to publish our lesson materials,
including the rich 3D
Puzzle World under a license
that will let you copy
and reuse our materials.
Incorporate your own ideas,
and help us reach many
audiences around the world.
So once a user has
created a Playground,
there's numerous ways
for sharing the results.
Playgrounds are simply
documents so you can share them
in all the usual ways
that you're familiar with.
And we didn't stop there.
We made it easier
to take pictures
of your program's output and
even incorporated replay kits
so that you can record
a coding session
and publish your
work as a video.
And for--
[ Applause ]
And for more advanced learners,
the Swift Playgrounds app
on the iPad and Xcode on the Mac
complement each other nicely.
You can move Playgrounds
back and forth
between the two environments
that eventually transition
into developing full
apps in the Xcode IDE.
And so that brings us
nicely to the next topic.
[ Applause ]
To tell you more about
Xcode, I'm going to hand
over to Matthew Furlich
[assumed spelling].
[ Applause ]
>> Thank you, Andreas.
Xcode 8 is a big release
with much to talk about,
so let's just jump right
in and start talking
about our Source Editor.
For this release, we focused
on adding the most
highly requested features
from all of you.
We started by adding in
active line highlighting,
and you can edit this color.
It'd work beautifully
with any Editor theme.
[ Applause ]
It gets better [laughter].
We also did a support
for Swift color literals
so you can now view and define
colors right in your source.
[ Applause ]
Let's go for three.
We added in Swift image literals
too so you can now view images
in your source and as
results for code completion.
And to help you write better
documentation, the editor has,
now has a command
to generate mark-up
for documenting your APIs.
[ Applause ]
So these features and a number
of usability improvements really
make Xcode's editing experience
awesome, but we didn't
want to stop there,
so we've added one more
feature, and it turns
out to be your number
one request.
App extensions.
[ Applause ]
With Xcode 8, we are
opening up the IDE.
We're starting with
source editing.
This extension works
with the active editor
to enable transformations,
changes in selection,
and navigation within the file.
And this opens up worlds of
opportunities for commands
such as reformatting,
commenting,
localizations, even to-do items.
Now, you can implement many
actions in each extension,
and each action is listed
as part of the Editor menu.
Users can set key buttons for
these actions too to enable them
as part of their workforce.
Now, as developers
of extensions--
[ Applause ]
As developers of
extensions, you can ship them
through the App Store or
deploy with Developer ID,
and these extensions
work in Xcode 8
on both Sierra and El Capitan.
[ Applause ]
Now, as a standard extension,
users can feel safe too.
These extensions are run
as a separate process
and have their signatures
verified.
And to further reinforce
safety, Xcode is now secured
by system integrity protection.
Which means only
trusted libraries
and extensions can interact
with the IDE and your code.
So the new source editing
extension is our first step
towards making Xcode an
even more extensible IDE.
We'd love to hear
your feedback on it
and other extensions
you'd like to see.
Now, we've also been
working on some improvements
to that way you learn
about code, and for that,
we have a brand new API
reference experience.
We've merged together
the API documentation
for our four platforms into
a single, unified reference.
Now, this reference
makes navigation easy,
working through frameworks
and symbols.
Now, searching the unified
reference means you see a single
result for each API and we've
integrated the same fuzzy
matching we use for code
completion and open quickly.
When browsing the reference,
the platform availabilities are
clearly listed for each API.
And in previous releases,
we ship this
as a separate download
because of its size.
With this release, we've
been able to shrink it
to almost one-tenth to
what it was previously,
so now we've included
it by default,
so you'll always have
the information you need.
[ Applause ]
Now, we also have some
great, new improvements
to Interface Builder, and I'd
like to show them
to you in a demo.
So here we have a project.
We're calling this Trailblazer.
It's a social application
for sharing your
favorite hiking trails.
Now, in addition to the way
that your interface is laid out,
you'll now notice that Interface
Builder is showing you the way
it's going to render
on a device.
Interface Builder now shows you
visual effects like vibrancy,
blurs, and shadows
right on the Canvas,
making a seamless experience for
designing and running your app.
You'll also notice that we're
displaying the interface
in the dimensions of a device,
and there's a new configuration
bar along the bottom
with common device sizes.
Here we're looking at
it in an iPhone 6s Plus.
I can select one of the other
items, like let me click on one
of the iPads, and I can see
how my interface will be
displayed there.
[ Applause ]
Here you see we've designed
an adaptive layout using two
columns on iPad.
To view it in other ways, I can
change the orientation if I want
to view it in landscape.
I can also view it in
one of the adaptations.
For example, let's look at it
in one-third size, which is used
for slide over as
for multitasking.
This is great because
it really allows me
to ensure I've implemented
the right interface
for all the ways users
will experience my app.
Now, we've also improved
the experience
for creating adaptive
layouts using size classes.
Let me give you an example.
The designers of this app wanted
to put an image, a button on top
of the image to show the hiking
trails overlaid on a map.
But because of the size
of the map, they only want
to do it on wider displays.
That's really easy.
In the configuration bar, I'll
click the Vary for Traits button
and I'm presented with the
two size class options,
Width and height.
iPhones and iPads differ
on the width size class,
so I'll check that option.
The configuration bar
turns blue to remind me
that I'm making customizations
for a specific size class.
But you'll also note the
list of devices have changed
to show me those devices
which will take advantage
of that customization.
Here I can see various iPads and
orientations and adaptations.
The last item, though, is the
iPhone 6s Plus in landscape.
That device and orientation
makes use
of the regular width size class,
and this is great information
because now I can ensure
I'm designing the interface
for the devices I intend.
I think our interface will look
great there, so let's go ahead
and make those changes.
I'll go into the library
and we'll grab a button out
and drag it into the interface.
If your hands weren't so sweaty,
you could grab the
button [laughter].
Come on.
Nobody look for a second.
This is not going to
be funny in a second.
[ Applause ]
There we go.
That should not be
the biggest applause.
Okay [laughter].
So let's continue on.
I'm going to delete the title
from this, and we'll go ahead
and set an image for it.
We'll make it this nice
compass icon we're given
and we'll just place
it correctly.
Now, I will connect up this
button a little bit later,
but let's make sure we got
the interface we wanted.
I'll click Done in
the configuration bar
and we'll switch back to the
iPhone 6s Plus in landscape.
Our button appears.
When I switch back to
portrait, it does not,
and that's exactly the
interface I wanted.
So Interface Builder
now makes it really easy
to design adaptive layouts.
The configuration bar is going
to show devices for
iOS and watchOS.
It also shows some
helpful options for tvOS.
I'll bring up the tvOS
version of our application,
and you'll see the configuration
bar now shows you options
for the light interface
and the dark interface.
And I can even make
customizations here too.
For example, let's
add a specialization
of the compass icon for
dark mode so that it pops
out a little bit better.
Now, there's one more feature
for Interface Builder
I'd like to show you.
You'll see that the tvOS
Storyboard is zoomed
out so it fits on the
entirety of the Canvas.
Interface Builder now
supports Canvas operations
at any zoom level.
[ Applause ]
So whether you want to
zoom all the way in,
get pixel perfect alignments,
or you want to zoom way back out
and work at an overview,
you can do it all.
[ Applause ]
And that's what we have
new for Interface Builder.
[ Applause ]
Thank you.
Designing in Interface Builder
now feels like working directly
on a device, and editing
at any zoom level means you're
no longer constrained by how big
or small those devices
really are.
For this release, we've also
focused on the accessibility
of our tools, and in particular,
we've made Interface Builder
work great with voiceover.
We've also completely rewritten
our AppleScript Dictionary,
making Xcode much
easier to integrate
with desktop automation.
[ Applause ]
Now, with each release, we add
additional support for finding,
diagnosing, and fixing issues.
And with Xcode 8, we are taking
another big step forward.
Over the last year, we've
added over 100 new diagnostics,
which provide great
insight as you build
and as you edit your
code with live issues.
We've added three new static
analyzers for localization,
malleability, and deallocation.
All common patterns that can
cause issues in your apps.
And we've continued to
invest in our testing system,
improving stability,
performance,
and adding some new options.
Xcode will now capture and
display logs for crashes
that occur during your testing.
[ Applause ]
This is a great option
because you can run your tests,
collect those logs, and
just like crash logs,
you can view them right in the
debugger to diagnose the issues.
We've also enhanced
xcodebuild with a new option
to run prebuilt tests.
[ Applause ]
Woo hoo, indeed.
It means this is perfect for
integrating scalable testing
with your own continuous
integration.
So now more than ever, Xcode
will help you with issues
as you build, analyze,
and test your apps.
But oftentimes some of
the most interesting,
if not let's say
diabolical, issues happen
when you run your code.
For that, we're introducing
something new called
Runtime Issues.
[ Applause ]
Runtime Issues are
like our others.
You're alerted to them
in the Activity view,
and you'll see details about
them in the Issue Navigator.
We've added a toggle at
the top to highlight them.
Now, there are three
kinds of runtime issues;
UI, threads, and memory.
Let's start with UI.
The View Debugger is already
a great tool for visualizing
and diagnosing problems
with your interface.
In addition to improved
accuracy and visual rendering,
the View Debugger will now
detect layout issues at runtime.
With each capture, the View
Debugger is able to detect views
with ambiguous layouts, and
these are caused by missing
and misconfigured constraints.
[ Applause ]
These issues are surfaced
right in the Navigator
and the Inspector provides
details to help you fix them.
Now, threading issues
are often unpredictable
and can be difficult to debug,
and there are many
potential causes.
Things like unlocking from the
wrong thread or data races.
To help you track down
these kinds of issues,
we're integrating Thread
Sanitizer into Xcode 8.
When enabled for
you application,
the Thread Sanitizer is able to
detect common threading problems
and will surface them
as runtime issues.
You can have Xcode break on
these issues as they occur
or you can collect them
all and review them
at the end of your session.
And the integrated report
provides a breakdown
of these issues,
giving you details
about any race conditions
and giving you stack
frames to help you navigate.
Like -- yes.
[ Applause ]
Now, like threading,
memory issues are often
challenging to identify and fix.
And to debug them effectively,
you often want to view a graph
of your objects and see how
they're all interconnected,
so that's what we
built [laughter].
New in Xcode 8 is a
memory debugger available
in the Debug bar here, which
will help you visualize
and navigate the object graph
for your running application.
[ Applause ]
Will you like it
better if I tell you
that it automatically
finds leaks too?
[ Applause ]
That's good because this
is an amazing new tool
for debugging memory issues,
and I'd like to show
it to you in a demo.
Okay, so here we have the
Trailblazer application.
I'm going to launch
it in the simulator.
Now, I was debugging
this earlier
and I noticed some memory
issues I wanted to look at.
I'll bring up the memory
report while we're doing this
and I'll click on the trail.
You'll see that memory spikes.
That one's okay.
I investigated that
early, and that's just
from loading all the
assets for the trail.
What I noticed, though, was
as I clicked on each review,
our memory spikes, and we
don't reclaim that memory,
even if we go back all the way
to the beginning
of our application.
This is generally indicative
of a memory management problem
and something we can use the
Memory Debugger to investigate,
so I'll click the Memory
Debugger button in the bar here,
and as we pause your
application,
we capture a graph
of the objects.
The debug navigator now shows
me all the objects allocated
in my application,
both those I created
and the ones the
system created for me.
I can filter this down
to only showing the items
from my project.
I can also type in a
string or an address
to look for specific objects.
Here I've typed in "controller"
and I see I have three instances
of the Comment View
Controller around.
That's surprising to me.
When I select any one of
them, we'll see a graph
for this object on the right.
Now, what you're seeing here
are all the reference paths
to this object that are
keeping it around in memory.
One of these objects I see here
is a Swift capture context.
This is somewhere in code
that my View Controller has been
captured as part of a closure.
That's a good place
to start looking.
I'll bring up the Inspector
to look at more details,
and one of the details we show
is the back trace to where
that capture happened.
And of course, I can just click
to navigate directly to the line
of code that caused it.
[ Applause ]
And I can see the
source of my problem.
I've set up an observer for
this View Controller to be told
when the rating changes.
This API returns an
observation token
that I see I've properly
cleared up down here
when the view goes away,
but I never retained
it in the first place.
That's a common and
simple mistake to make.
It's also one the Memory
Debugger makes really easy
to find and fix.
Now, I mentioned before the
Memory Debugger also finds
leaks, and it's alerting
me to three I have
up here in the Activity view.
I'll click on that and be
taken to the Issue Navigator
where I see three types
of objects I'm leaking.
An array, user review,
and user objects.
I'll click on one of the
reviews, I'm sorry, the users,
and now we see the
reference cycle.
A user has an array of
written reviews, and each one
of those user reviews has a
reference back to that user.
If all these references
are strongly held,
this will leak all
over those objects.
Now, it looks like I'm
leaking them all uniformly.
If I wanted more details though
on any one of these objects,
I can use the context menu
to print something right
to the console or just bring
up a quick look to
see more details.
Now, in this case, the reviewing
user relationship is the one I
want to investigate, and we'll
just navigate just like code.
I'll just command click on it
and be taken right to the line
of code where that
reference came from.
And sure enough, I forgot
to declare that as weak.
So just like that, the
Memory Debugger was able
to show me the leaks I
had and help me fix them.
[ Applause ]
So that's the new Memory
Debugger in Xcode 8.
Now, there is one other kind
of issue I'd like to talk
about today, and that's
with provisioning.
[ Applause ]
There is nothing more
frustrating when you're working
on your projects than having
issues with code signing.
Well, actually, that turns
out to not quite be true
because in some cases, the
solution was more frustrating
than the problem itself.
[ Laughter & Applause ]
So we addressed this in Xcode 8
and we've completely rebuilt
our provisioning system.
[ Applause ]
We started by creating new
signing actions that are faster,
more robust, and built with
new Xcode workflows in mind.
We generated a new
user interface elements
to clearly show you
the profile, team,
and certificate you're using
and clearly show you any issues.
We refined our messages
to ensure they always
included actionable information
and we also were ensuring to
generate a log of the requests
and the results to
be transparent
about what's occurring.
Based on these, we had a
strong foundation on which
to provide two new
provisioning workflows.
Xcode 8 has an option for
automatic code signing.
With this code signing
option, Xcode takes care of all
of the details using
a dedicated profile,
and this profile is
separate from any
that you create or manage.
We'll take care of all
the signing requests
for adding entitlements
and regenerating new items.
For cases where you
would like more control
of your signing setup, you
can disable this option
and use Customized Code Signing.
[ Applause ]
With Customized Code Signing,
you can specify the exact
signing assets you would
like to use and you can specify
them per build configuration,
which is a great option when you
have a variety of signing needs.
[ Applause ]
Customized Code Signing
still takes advantage
of our new foundations to
give you great feedback
and assistance for any issues.
And there's one other area of
provisioning that we wanted
to focus on, which was
development certificates.
To make development easier when
working with many machines,
Xcode now supports multiple
development certificates.
[ Applause ]
This means when you
get a new Mac,
you just add your
Apple ID and that's it.
You no longer need to revoke
or share a certificate from any
of your other development.
[ Applause ]
So the new provisioning system,
automatic and customized signing
and multiple development
certificates.
Always that Xcode 8
makes provisioning easy
and gives you the
control you need.
And in this release, we
focused on performance,
and we have some great
achievements for you.
Compared to the release we
shipped just a year ago,
you'll find Xcode launches
twice as fast all the way
up to being 50 times faster
at the indexing of tests.
[ Applause ]
These improvements all add
up to make Xcode 8 something
that is fast and fun to use.
So these have been some
of the many features
and enhancements
you'll find in Xcode 8.
Please come by the
labs this week
and let us know what you think.
Next, I'd like to invite
up Sebastien Marineau-Mes,
who's going to give you some
information about exciting,
new platform technologies.
Sebastien [applause]?
>> Thank you, Matthew.
Thank you.
Let me now give an
update on a number of key,
foundational technologies,
and I'm going
to start with compression.
Now, if you recall, last
year, we introduced lzfse
as our new mainstream
compression.
At three times the
speed of zlib and less
than half the energy
consumption,
it's a really compelling
technology
and one that's seen
great adoption.
Now, today we're announcing
that we're open-sourcing
lzfse, and we [applause]--
There you go.
And we believe that this will
encourage further adoption,
especially for multiplatform
and backhand offline
compression use cases.
Next, I'd like to
talk about networking.
Now, we know that
the performance
of some applications
really depends
on having a great
network connection,
but today's networks don't
really have a great way
to prioritize the traffic
that's most important.
For example, people
downloading YouTube cat videos
at work can interfere
with your really important
video conference.
And so in working with Cisco,
we've added intelligence
to the network, and what
the network is now able
to do is identify
those trusted devices.
Identify those applications
that are most important
to your business, and then
prioritize that traffic end
to end throughout the network.
Which gives you much
better performance
for those applications that
are most important to you.
That is networking.
Next--
[ Applause ]
Next, let's talk about logging.
Now, logging is a
technology that all
of you use during
development, debugging,
and for field diagnostics.
Traditionally, logging
has been very fragmented.
A number of you roll
your own solutions.
The solutions that are available
in the platform are often slow,
and so this year, we've
set out to rethink logging,
and we've come up
with a technology
that we think is
very compelling.
It's unified.
It's extremely fast.
It's very compact on how
it stores data on disc.
It also gives you enough
flexibility to support logging
across applications,
daemons, system services.
It has this concept
of in-memory tracing
where you can capture very
high-frequency log messages
that only get persisted to disc
when your application
actually hits an air condition.
And finally, we've
baked privacy right in,
so you can capture very rich
log messages during development
and have those be
automatically redacted
when you ship your application
through end customers.
Now, along with this
[applause] --
We have rewritten the console
application it is much richer
in capability.
It gives you, for example,
the ability to live stream
through development devices,
the ability to advance filtering
and grade system
introspection capabilities,
so that is the new logging.
Next up--
[ Applause ]
Next up, let's talk
about file systems.
All right.
Now, of course, HFS Plus is the
mainstream file system on Macs,
and it was first
released in 1998.
Today it's deployed
across every Apple product,
over a billion devices.
And of course, HFS Plus was
designed over 18 years ago,
and I think it's really a
testament to the strength
of its original design that
it's still a compelling file
system today.
But of course, when it was
designed, we had floppy drives
on Macs, and so we thought
now may be the time for us
to launch a new file system.
And so today we're announcing
brand new Apple File System.
[ Applause ]
There you go.
I thought you guys
might be excited by this
or the crowd might be excited.
Now, the Apple File
System is scalable
from our smallest device, the
watch, to high-end Mac Pros
with very large storage
configurations.
It's also modern.
We designed it first
and foremost for today
and tomorrow's storage
technologies, Flash and SSD.
It's resilient and we've
used the opportunity
to unify encryption
across iOS and Mac OS,
which gives us great
flexibility going forward.
Now, the Apple File System has a
number of new, unique features,
and I want to highlight
two of them for you.
The first is called cloning.
Now, why cloning?
It turns out that if you look
at a system that's been running
for a while, you'll find many
duplicates of identical files.
It's kind of human nature
to copy things around.
That's of course inefficient.
It uses up storage space.
But with clones, you're able
to copy files and only pay
for that initial storage when
the files are actually modified.
It's very fast and you can
clone files, directories,
and directory hierarchies.
The second feature that I want
to highlight is called
Snapshots.
Now, what are Snapshots?
They're really an
image of the content
of the file system
at a point in time.
Why would you want this?
Well, let's say you're
creating a backup application.
Using Snapshots, you can go
and back up a consistent view
of the file system
at a point in time.
Another great example of
where this is useful is
in the classroom.
You may set up a device for
your students that has content,
configuration files,
applications,
and so on that you're going
to use during a class.
As the students use a device,
they may inadvertently modify
the content or the settings,
and what you can do is you
can use Snapshots at the end
of the class to revert
the device back
to its original state
so that it's ready
for the next class of students.
Now, these are features of
the new Apple File System
with a developer
preview of it that's part
of the Mac OS Sierra release
available to you today.
We'd encourage you all to
download it, check it out,
give us feedback, and the Apple
File System will be coming
to all Apple devices soon.
[ Applause ]
All right.
Finally, let's talk
about privacy.
You heard about a new, powerful
technique called differential
privacy in this morning's
keynote, and I will attempt
to explain that to you.
I will start with the formal
math behind differential privacy
and remind, just note that
while it does look complex,
I can guarantee you the
math actually works.
And I'm going to actually
instead explain it
to you using a couple
of examples.
So the first example
is we're going
to use differential privacy
to try to resolve once
and for all one of
the most controversial
and important questions
of modern computer science
code formatting [laughter].
This is of course an
important question.
We're going to poll our audience
to get the answer to this.
It's also something that is
where you want your answer
to remain private
because let's face it,
some of your coworkers may be
pretty passionate about this.
So how do we do this using
differential privacy?
Well, first, each of you
would provide your preference,
but before we send that over to
Apple to aggregate the results
of the survey, through
differential privacy,
we add noise to each answer.
And after we've added noise,
we actually have no way
to know what you
originally answered.
We send this to Apple,
and the beauty
of differential privacy is that
after we aggregate this data
over a large population,
we're actually able
to recover the answer
to our question.
Now, I'm not going
to pass judgment
on this, the actual answer.
It looks like of course
we're still very divided
in our opinions on this,
but I will remind everyone
that after you've run your
code through the compiler,
this doesn't actually really
matter, so [laughter] that's --
[ Applause ]
Now, how are we actually
applying differential privacy
in iOS X?
Let me give an example of this.
In Spotlight, we provide
suggestions for deep links
and we'd of course like to
surface the most relevant
and popular suggestions
to our end users.
And so the way that we do
this, we assign to each
of our deep links a unique
hash, and as users navigate
on their device, whenever
they encounter a deep link,
we take that hash, add noise
to it, extract a fragment
of it, and send it to Apple.
Now, any one of these fragments
on their own is completely
meaningless,
but when we aggregate this
across our entire user base,
we're able to recover the
popularity of our deep links
and then use that to
surface them in Spotlight
and improve our user's
experience.
That is the science behind
differential privacy.
There's one more aspect of it
though that I want to touch on.
You might think, well, if we're
capturing samples from users
and this works by capturing
many samples from many users,
what happens if Apple captures
too many samples from one user?
Could you not then
figure out what I'm doing?
And this is where the
privacy budget comes in.
The privacy budget limits
the amount of samples
that we can capture from any
given user and it ensures
that in the end, we can
never recover any meaningful
information from any
one of our users.
So that is differential privacy.
It's a powerful technique
that allows us to learn
from our users, improve
user experience,
and still maintain your privacy.
So with this, I'm going to hand
it over to Toby, Toby Paterson,
who will be talking about
higher level features in iOS X.
Toby?
>> Thanks, Sebastien.
[ Applause ]
Good afternoon.
There we go.
So, you know, it's really thanks
to all of you that we have
such a rich ecosystem on iOS,
and we are constantly looking
for new ways to help
users find applications,
get into the apps
they like to use,
and to integrate
your applications
across the rest of the OS.
You saw earlier how your
app can propagate virally
through messages, and
we're making it really easy
to tell people about your
application right here
from the home screen.
We've added a new Share button
to the Quick Actions List.
This brings up the Share Sheet,
and so now you can Tweet your
application to the whole world,
and this is available for
free in every application.
Now, we have a lot of ways
that we try to get users
into the right app at
just the right time.
I'm going to move through them
quickly, so bear with me here.
Handoff lets you carry on a
task from one device to another.
Spotlight can link directly
to your application content.
A Universal Link will take you
to the most appropriate place
for a platform, and
you can link directly
from one application to another.
Siri will suggest apps here in
Today view and in Spotlight.
We can suggest an app
at just the right time
in the App Switcher
on the lock screen.
We can connect apps based
on common data types
like this and this and this.
Well, I think you get the idea.
There's only one thing I really
want you to take away from all
of this, which is that
NSUserActivity is your gateway
to a whole ton of functionality.
It's how your application tells
the OS what people are doing
in your app, and that allows us
to create intelligent
suggestions and connections
between your applications.
And in iOS X, we're adding two
important pieces of information.
Now, many apps use addresses
in a variety of ways,
and we can use that
to make connections
between your applications.
Let me illustrate
with an example.
This is the Yelp page for one
of my favorite restaurants
in San Francisco.
Now, suppose it were to
provide an NSUserActivity
with this address on it.
That would allow me to do things
like asking Siri to
just take me here.
My phone knows that I use
Uber a lot to get around,
and it can make it
really easy for me
to order a ride directly
to the restaurant.
Or when I'm typing in a text
field that's expecting location
data, QuickType can suggest an
address that I was just looking
at and Maps can include that in
its list of suggestions along
with a quick way of getting
back into the application.
Now, we also interact with
people in a variety of ways,
and the OS can learn which
app I use to communicate
with any given person.
To do this, your app needs
to give us three
pieces of information.
Enough context so that
we can find an entry
in the address book for this
person, the kind of service
that you're providing, that's a
messages or video chat platform,
and the specific
identifier or handle
that you'll use for this person.
Now, this is the new
Address Book card,
which we're making available a
lot more prominently throughout
the OS, and you'll notice that
we can automatically include
in here information that we
learned from your applications.
Now, when I tap on one of these
new Quick Communication buttons
at the top of the card, we
can also include your app
in the list of options.
When I make my choice,
we'll remember that so
that the next time
when I tap this button,
we can take you straight
into the application.
I should point out that all
of this learning is private
to the user and accessible
only on their devices.
Now, we deeply believe
that integrating your apps
across the OS makes for a
much richer user experience.
Extensions, of course,
are how you do that,
and you've heard earlier
about the new iMessage Apps,
Maps extensions, and SiriKit.
Well, I'd like to
tell you a little bit
about two extension points that
we're adding to Notifications.
A service extension runs in
the background and allows you
to modify the push payload
before we show the notification
to the user.
It lets you do things like
downloading an image, a video,
or an audio file
in the background
and embedding it directly
in the notification.
Or you could encrypt your
push payload on your server
and use a service extension to
decrypt it locally on device,
providing for full
end-to-end encryption.
[ Applause ]
Now, I should point
out you may want
to use something
a little stronger
than the ROT13 algorithm
that we're proposing here.
We're going to double
ROT13 it next year
for extra security [laughter].
Now, if you want an even
richer user experience,
a content extension can provide
an arbitrary view that we'll use
for the expanded look
of a notification.
This lets you provide a dynamic
and interactive experience
that's really tailored
to your application.
This morning, you got a quick
tour of the revamped Today view
with its vibrant,
new look for widgets.
Now, a widget can still
be any size you want
within reasonable limits,
but we're also adding a new,
compact, fixed size to optimize
for better information density.
And the thing that
we're really excited
about is making these
widgets available right here
from the home screen.
I'm going to tell you
what you need to do
to get this functionality
in your widgets.
The first thing you want to do
is probably update your look
and support the new compact size
so that your widget
doesn't look too funny.
You need to build with the
iOS X SDK, and that's it.
Nothing else has changed about
how you build your widgets.
You just get this new
functionality for free,
and so we're really excited.
We think this is going to
open up a whole new dimension
into your application.
Okay, let's switch gears
now and talk about the Mac.
So Mac OS Sierra is adding full
support for localizing your apps
in right-to-left languages,
including reversing UI elements
in places where that
makes sense.
The Mac now joins
with iOS and watchOS,
which quietly introduced support
for this earlier in the year.
And with so many potential
customers all over the world,
it's really more important
now than ever before
that your app be properly
localized and internationalized.
And you can learn
more about that here.
Now, you know, when Sebastien
first started talking about tabs
versus spaces, we were
pretty sure this was
where he was going.
You saw this morning how
people can gather together all
of their windows into
a single tabbed UI.
AppKit will take care of pretty
much everything here for you
and it's smart enough not to
pair your preferences windows
with your document windows,
and so on and so forth.
And in fact, if you're
using NSDocument,
there really is nothing
else that you need
to do in your application.
If you're not using
NSDocument, there's a little bit
of API you need to adopt to
support creating a new tab,
but I'd really encourage
you to take a look
at whether NSDocument isn't
appropriate for your use case.
You see, we also showed you this
morning how we're making it easy
for people to move their
documents and their data
into the cloud, and
we really believe
that this is the
future of file storage.
So it's super important that
your app adopt best practices
in terms of file
coordination and metadata query.
And here too if you're using
NSDocument, it will take care
of pretty much all the
heavy lifting for you,
along with UIDocument
as counterpart on iOS.
Now, I have an important
update for you about iCloud.
As you know, the iCloud
APIs are available on all
of our platforms,
but on the Mac,
use of these APIs has
been restricted just
to those apps distributed
via the Mac App Store.
Well, in Mac OS Sierra, we're
removing that restriction.
[ Applause ]
Now, your app still
needs to be signed
with a valid developer ID, which
by the way, will also get rid
of those pesky, untrusted
developer alerts.
But once you've done
that, you can use all
of these API no matter how
you distribute your app
to your customers.
Next, CloudKit.
We introduced CloudKit two years
ago, and it's the foundation
that we use for building all
of our new cloud services.
Now, it has a fairly
coarse-grained permission model.
Either your data could
be accessed by everybody
in the world or it's restricted
to just a single user.
Well, the new CloudKit
sharing feature opens that up
and gives your app
explicit control
over who can access your data.
[ Applause ]
The new CKShare class gives
you a, governs the permissions,
who can read and write
a given set of records,
and this API is available
on all of our platforms.
On the Mac and on iOS,
we're providing standard UI
for taking care of the
mechanics of inviting people
and managing people
in your application.
We use CloudKit sharing for
the new collaboration features
that we've built into Notes,
and I encourage you to check it
out in the developer
preview today.
With that, I'd like to hand off
to Josh Shaffer [assumed
spelling],
who's going to give you
some updates on watchOS.
Thank you.
[ Applause ]
>> Thanks, Toby.
As you heard in the keynote,
watchOS 3 simplifies navigation
and optimizes performance.
These improvements go
beyond just the system level
and include many enhancements
to the apps as well.
These enhancements focus
on three key qualities
for Watch apps.
The first is that
they be glanceable.
Individual interactions
with Apple Watch are short,
so it's important to
present well-designed,
simple information to
the user, focusing just
on what's most relevant to make
sure that it's easy to digest.
The second is that
they be actionable.
Now, this includes
simplifying access
to the most common actions
taken on the watch itself.
For example, we've
redesigned the Fitness app
to reduce the number of steps
necessary to start a workout.
It also means simplifying
access to key information
that your users will
want to act on even
if they won't take the
action on the watch itself.
And the third is ensuring that
your apps remain responsive
by keeping them up to
date and ready to act
as soon as they're needed.
Sure, thanks [laughs].
I agree. Okay, so when you think
about an app, the first thing
that may come to mind is an app
that takes up the full screen.
Now, that's definitely part
of it, but on Apple Watch,
it's important to keep in
mind that your app has access
to two other great
interfaces in the form
of complications
and notifications.
So these three interfaces are
just three different views
into your one app,
so it's important
that they present
consistent information.
When you update any one of
them, you'll want to update all
of them because if they're
displaying different
information, then your users
won't trust any of them.
Now, you may remember
that in watchOS 2,
there was a fourth
interface called Glances.
Glances provided
simple access to the,
a summary of your
favorite apps' information.
In watchOS 3, this functionality
is now provided by the new Dock
and is instantly
accessible from anywhere
with just a press
of the side button.
If your watchOS 2 app
included a Glance,
that separate interface is no
longer necessary in watchOS 3,
but its simple design can help
you update the primary interface
for your application to
make sure that it looks
and works great when
viewed from the Dock.
Apps in the Dock are instantly
responsive, helping to make sure
that the most common tasks taken
on the watch can be accomplished
in just a couple of seconds.
Now, that's obviously a very
short time, but striving
for it can be a great guide
in helping you design the
top-level features of your apps
to make sure that they work
really well on Apple Watch.
While each individual
interaction is short,
some apps may be
used multiple times
over a longer period of time.
For example, I may refer back
to my shopping list many
times while I'm at the store.
In watchOS 3, each
time I raise my wrist,
I can instantly see the
items I still need to get
and check off the ones
I've already picked up.
It's now really easy to design
apps that have this kind
of interaction model because
watchOS 3 will return you
to the last app that you were
using for up to 8 minutes
after you last used it.
Once you're done using it,
you'll be returned
to the watch face.
[ Applause ]
When your app's not in use,
ensuring that it stays
responsive means keeping it
up to date in the
background so that it's ready
when you do want to use it.
To make this really easy,
watchOS 3 includes
a brand new set
of Background App Refresh APIs.
Background App Refresh
is a critical part
of building responsive
watchOS applications,
and periodically
updating your app
in the background can be a great
enhancement no matter what type
of app you're building.
Now, if you're building a
fitness app, for these types
of apps, it's even more
important that they remain
up to date for the entire
duration of the workout,
so we have some additional
enhancements just for them.
During a workout session, these
apps will now run continually
in the background even
while the screen is off,
ensuring that they can
monitor workout progress
and provide updates to the user
when they reach key
milestones using haptics.
During the workout, they also
remain instantly available even
if you switch to another
app to perform another task.
So if I jump out to the Music
app to change the current track,
after I've dropped my wrist,
I'll very shortly be
returned back to my workout.
We've also enhanced the
access to the heart rate
and accelerometer sensors
so that they now
provide continuous values
for the entire duration
of the workout as well.
[ Applause ]
In addition to these
sensor enhancements,
we've also got a whole bunch of
great, new hardware access APIs.
Crown events give you raw
access to rotation events
from the Digital Crown.
Gesture recognizers
make it really easy
to add custom tap interactions
to your apps, touch interactions
such as tap, swipe,
and pan, and of course,
the gyroscope is
now also accessible
in addition to the
accelerometer.
[ Applause ]
To make sure that you can do
really cool things with all
of these hardware access APIs,
we've also brought a bunch
of graphics and media
frameworks to the watchOS SDK.
SpriteKit and SceneKit give
you a ton of flexibility
to enhance the visuals
of your applications
and also your notifications.
AV Foundation makes it
really easy to play sounds
out of the watch
speaker, and in the spirit
of simplifying navigation
in your apps,
you can now play
video back inline
in your application
interfaces as well [applause].
Of course, you also
often need to get data on
and off the watch, and
to help make that easier,
as Toby mentioned, CloudKit is
now part of the watchOS SDK.
Because it's built on top of
NSURL session, it works even
when your phone's not present
and your watch is near
a known Wi-Fi network.
Apple Watch is already a great
way to pay for physical goods
in stores, and in watchOS 3,
you can now offer physical goods
for sale within your
own apps to be purchased
with just a double-tap
of the side button.
Building a great watch app
is just the first step.
It's also important that
you make it easy for users
to discover and install
your apps.
And to help you with that,
the new watch face gallery
in iOS X includes an
entire section devoted just
to displaying all of your apps.
With just a few simple steps,
you can create a complication
bundle which enables your app
to appear in the
watch face gallery.
It's the first thing that
a new watch owner will see
after they've paired
their watch,
and it displays the
complications
from all their favorite
apps that they use
on their iPhone every day.
This makes it really easy for
them to get their apps installed
and added right to
their watch face.
We've been working really hard
to give you all the tools you
need to build great, glanceable,
actionable, and responsive
apps, and we can't wait
to see what you're
going to do with them.
To give you some ideas
of how this can help
enhance your apps on watchOS.
Eliza Block will now come
up and give us a demo
of Background App Refresh and
some of the new graphics APIs.
Eliza?
[ Applause ]
>> Hi. So I have here an
application that I built
for watchOS 2, which shows
Max the panda, my friend,
and it tells me what his
mood is at different times.
So right now, you can
see that he's happy.
If I now suspend the app,
you can see that I have a
complication also telling me
that he's happy, but here is
a notification that tells me
that suddenly Max
has become hungry.
Now, this app for watchOS
2 has a few problems
which I'm going to show you now.
The first is that when I
dismiss the notification,
my complication has not
updated to reflect the fact
that Max is now hungry.
And even worse, when I go
into the Dock, the snapshot
of the app in the Dock also
has not updated, so I'm failing
to show a unified set of data
across all the interfaces
to my app.
So going now to the code,
there's a really easy way new
in watchOS 3 to address
these issues.
In my extension delegate, I
have a single funnel point,
Handle Background Tasks,
which is the perfect place
to update all of these
interfaces as my data changes.
Here in my Snapshot
Refresh background task,
I'm going to add just
two lines of code
to address both of
these problems.
The first is to update
my interface
for my current friend's
status, and second,
I'm going to also reload
my complication as well
when the snapshot is taken.
Okay, so that should address
the problems that we saw.
But while we're in here,
let me make this app a little
bit more fun because as you saw,
Max was kind of just a
static image in watchOS 2.
But in watchOS 3, we can
incorporate a SceneKit scene
to make some animation happen.
So I'm going to switch
over here to my interface,
and here's my application
interface.
I'm going to delete the image
and drag in a SceneKit scene.
Now, I wrote a tiny bit
of code earlier just
to populate this scene
with some SceneKit assets
and to make an outlet, which
I'll connect right now.
Drag it into my SceneKit
interface.
Now, not only can you
add a SceneKit scene
to your application itself,
but you can also add one
to the notification, which
will be a lot more fun
than a text-based notification.
I'm going to drag one
into there as well.
I need to resize
this a little bit.
Hook it up to the outlet.
All right, and with those
changes, I'm going to go ahead
and run this application again,
and we'll hopefully see
something a little bit more
dynamic this time.
So here we have a much
happier looking version
of Max running around, and when
I now suspend the application,
wait for him to get hungry.
We see a really sad,
more convincing version
of Max rubbing his tummy.
[ Applause ]
So I think this is
a lot more fun.
When I dismiss the notification,
my complication has updated
as we hoped to reflect his
current status, and if I look
in the Dock, you can see
that the snapshot has also
now been updated to reflect
that he's hungry
and no longer happy.
So that's just a few of the
new things you can do which,
with the new APIs in watchOS 3.
We're excited to see
what you guys build.
And next up, I'd like
to invite Jim Young
to the stage to talk about tvOS.
[ Applause ]
>> Thanks, Eliza.
We've been super excited
since bringing the App Store
to Apple TV just
this last October
because we believe the future
of TV is apps, and since then,
you guys have been very
busy bringing over 6000 apps
to the App Store, including
entertainment apps, games,
health and fitness, and
education apps, and many more.
So let's talk about what it
means to develop on tvOS.
First, it's already
familiar to you.
You use all the tools and
languages you already know.
And tvOS includes the
essential frameworks
that you're familiar
with from iOS.
Plus, we've got some
new frameworks specific
to tvOS that we've built.
There's all the foundational
support you need
for building great apps.
We have a rich media stack
for audio/video apps.
And of course, we've got
excellent support for games.
And we're bringing even more
features to the platform.
With PhotoKit, you can now
create these great apps
that showcase users'
photos on their big screen,
and we've made it super easy to
add support for light and dark,
excuse me, our light/dark
appearance.
So it's a rich set
of technologies,
and this is just a partial list.
There's a whole lot more.
Let's talk about using
all these technologies
and bringing them all together
to deliver a great
experience on tvOS.
And I want to start with Touch.
When designing tvOS,
we knew we wanted
to bring a first-class Touch
experience into the living room.
Now, Touch needs to feel
fluid and connected.
It needs to be predictable.
It needs to be fun.
That's a particular
challenge in the living room
when the TV's 10 feet away.
So let's look at
how we solve this.
We have updated UIKit
so that all the controls
and views look beautiful
on the big screen.
We've added UIFocus to allow
you to indicate which elements
of your UI are focusable.
And we have updated
UIMotionEffect so it takes input
from the focus engine.
Now, altogether this
provides a direct connection
between what the user
is doing with the remote
and what they see
on the big screen.
Good news here is that we've
done all the heavy lifting
for you.
Your UIKit apps will get
all of this for free.
Now, if you have a
server-based app,
apps used to deliver content.
We've got a lot of great apps
like this one from Showtime.
We have a technology
called TVMLKit,
a framework called TVMLKit.
TVMLKit is a new, high-level
framework we built specifically
for tvOS.
It's built on top of
UIKit so you get all
that connective Touch
experience that we just showed.
We provide a large
set of templates,
and you can even provide
your own custom templates
and native controls.
TVMLKit has allowed teams
to build these beautiful,
highly stylized, customized
apps in a short amount of time.
Let's now talk about how you can
extend the experience outside
of Apple TV by integrating
with other Apple devices.
One easy thing to do is
to save app and game state
in the cloud using CloudKit.
Making it easier for users to
start a game on their Apple TV
and pick it up and resume
right where they left off
on their iPhone or iPad.
We've also seen some great apps
that use multiple Apple
devices at the same time.
With SongPop Party
from FreshPlanet,
the whole family can
play using their iPhone
to answer music trivia
questions.
And to make it even easier
to create apps that talk
to each other across devices,
we're bringing Multipeer
Connectivity to the platform.
Just a few lines of code--
[ Applause ]
Just a few lines of code,
you can easily connect
to your apps running
on a different device.
Now, this morning, we announced
the new Apple TV Remote app.
Now everyone in your household
that has an iPhone can have an
Apple TV Remote in their hands.
To your apps it looks
and behaves just
like the Siri Remote, but
we've added a couple features
to take advantage of the screen.
The Now Playing screen provides
a full set of playback controls
as well as cover
art for your media.
Just like showing art and
controls on the iOS lock screen,
use the Media Player Remote
-- I always get this one --
Media Player Remote Command API
to add this information
to Remote app.
The app also provides a
screen designed for gameplay.
To your game, the new app shows
up as a micro gamepad
just like the Siri Remote.
To take advantage of multiple
micro gamepads, you need to opt
in by setting an Info.plist key.
In addition to Siri Remote
and the new Remote app,
tvOS also supports
MFi game controllers.
And coming this fall,
tvOS will also support
up to four simultaneous
game controllers.
[ Applause ]
But we didn't want
to stop there.
We wanted to enable
even more awesome games.
We wanted to enable games
that might require these kind
of controllers, so
we're happy to announce
that we're updating
our controller policy.
You can narrow your games to
require a game controller.
[ Applause ]
tvOS will check if the
required controller is present
and prompt the user
if it's necessary.
That's an update on tvOS.
We're super happy to be here.
We've got a lot of
labs and sessions
with the tvOS engineers there,
so please come by and stop by.
Next, I want to introduce
Geoff Stahl is going to come up
and talk about graphics
technologies.
Geoff?
[ Applause ]
>> Thanks, Jim.
So I'm going to talk
about graphics.
I'm going to talk about a
couple areas of graphics.
We have really great
things to talk about today,
and I'll start with color.
So we're building
astonishing new displays
for our latest iPads and
Macs, ones that are capable
of reproducing absolutely
stunning color.
In fact, as DisplayMate says,
"The color accuracy is visually
indistinguishable from perfect."
So how do we do this?
Well, this is all
about color gamut.
So most displays are built
with the sRGB color gamut,
which is narrow and doesn't
reproduce all the colors you
would see in life accurately
of things like flowers
or paint colors or maybe
even the clothes you wear.
So we're moving to the wide P3
color gamut, which contributes
to our ability to really
accurately reproduce
and render these
real-life objects.
But we're not stopping there.
We're going to go
all in on color.
From our system APIs to
our system applications,
we support deep and
wide color throughout.
And if you're an
application using UIImageView
or UIView, you get it for free.
You get it automatically.
If you have to manipulate wide
colors yourself synthetically,
we also offer APIs for that.
And of course, we have
a great capture story.
Our latest cameras support
capturing deep and wide color.
We have APIs to access
raw images.
And we can also now capture
with APIs LivePhotos.
So that's color.
[ Applause ]
I'd like to talk
about technology now
that's changed the direction
of industry, and that's Metal.
Metal we introduced
two years ago
and has been wildly successful.
And keep in mind, when
we developed Metal,
when we enhance it, we enhance
it with our devices in mind.
Which allows us to innovate
in a rapid pace with things
like Metal tessellation that
allows high-order surfaces
for rendering accuracy
like never before
or Metal function
specialization.
Which when combined with S
code allows you to build a set
of shaders that automatically
handling your material
and lighting properties
in your scene.
And for things like
memoryless render targets,
which use the architecture
of our Tile cash
to reduce the amount
of memory used
in your application
or resource use.
Which allows your application
to specialize the way it handles
memory within a Metal app.
And Metal is everywhere.
Hundreds of millions
of devices use Metal.
Our key graphics frameworks
and major game engines
are built on top of it.
So whether you're
using a high-level API
or programming directly
to Metal itself,
you get all the performance
optimizations we've built in.
Another thing about Metal,
it's one of our foundational
technologies
of our games ecosystem.
So let's talk about games.
Over the past few years, we've
built a great games ecosystem,
and the goal of this is to
build the APIs and tools
which allow you to take
your ideas in gaming
and turn them into reality.
I want to cover some
highlights here today.
First, as mentioned this
morning, Replay Kit.
We introduced Replay
Kit last year,
and it's really super
easy to adopt.
It allows your users to start
a recording, play their game,
edit that recording, and then
share with their friends.
Well, this year, we're
going to take it up a notch
with ReplayKit Streaming.
Now, Replay Kit can
live stream to services
that support the ReplayKit
Streaming Extension.
This allows your users to not
just go from, not just share
with their friends
but stream live
to the internet automatically
with ReplayKit Live Streaming.
And the -- absolutely.
[ Applause ]
And even better, it's about
three lines of code to adopt
if you already use Replay Kit.
This is super easy and could
really expand the social reach
of your applications.
So speaking of social, let's
talk about Game Center.
We're changing the way that
Game Center Multiplayer works.
Now with our latest OS's,
you can invite anyone you
can send a message to.
So your users can invite
anyone they can reach
out via message,
and it is that easy.
It's just as easy as
sending a message.
And the cool thing here is if
you're already using the games
that are multiplayer APIs,
you don't need to do anything.
With the latest OS's,
this just works,
and we're not going
to stop with that.
We're going to add new
APIs to Game Center.
Game Center Sessions.
Game Center Sessions creates a
persistent, shared experience
where users can come and go.
This means you can design your
games with the mobile user
in mind the way they come and go
into your application that's
allowing a new paradigm
in multiplayer gaming
in the mobile space.
Finally, GameplayKit.
GameplayKit is our
component-based API
that allows you to instance
and customize these components
and make the building blocks
for your game objects,
letting us do the
heavy lifting for you.
And I'd like to invite Norman
Wang on stage to give a demo
of these components and
our Xcode gameplay tools.
[ Applause ]
>> Thanks, Geoff.
I'd like to show you how quickly
I can build a game in Xcode 8.
Here's a game project
I'm currently working on.
It's a competitive
game involving a hero
and enemies throwing paint
balloons at each other.
Now, I have been using the
new APIs from SpriteKit
and GameplayKit this year.
As you can see, the game
needs three major elements
to be ready; a map, a hero,
and the gameplay pieces.
I have already implemented the
hero's movement and animation,
but it is clearly
missing the collision
with the island bounds, so
let's go ahead and fix that.
Opening our Xcode
project and looking
at the source code section,
I have already written a
few gameplay behaviors using
GKComponent provided
by GameplayKit,
like the fight component here.
And in Xcode 8, I
can now expose any
of my class properties
that's defined in my class
to the 2D editor then I can
customize whenever the behavior
gets attached to one
entity in the scene.
So to build the island map,
I've been using the
new Tiled Map Editor.
So in my game, there's
three different tile sets
that I have specified.
There's sand, water, and grass.
Not only do I have the ability
to specify both the interior
and exterior tiles, I can
also introduce variance.
So here for the red
edge, for example,
for this individual tile image,
if I want to add a new look
to it to get rid of the small
rock, I can simply just drag it
in from the Media Library.
And now this tile
set is complete.
Let me go ahead and show
you how I can use this.
So switching back to the island
map, the island is constructed
with the new tile map
functionality with,
provided by SpriteKit, so
to make a modification,
I can simply select
the tile map.
Make a double click, and
select the active tile
that I want to work on.
Now that I think the island
looks a little bit too plain,
and to make such modifications,
I can just simply paint
across the level and Xcode will
automatically paint the correct
tiles to make it with
surrounding neighbors.
It's that easy.
So now I think I got the look
I'm going after with the island.
Let's look at some of the
gameplay elements here.
To power the hero, our hero's
movement and animation,
I have already attached
the player input component
and the move component.
And to make the player
respect the island boundaries,
I can simply add a collision
component to have implemented.
So this way, it will
automatically create a physics
body for our hero
and the islands based
on the current tile sets
that's being set up.
And to give the player
the ability
to throw the water balloons,
I can simply add the
fight component to it.
And notice here how the
health property being exposed
by the fight component
class is now visible.
I can give it a custom
value here.
So for example, I can set
the value to be 2 rather
than using the default
value of 1.
And in addition, I have
a drone that drops the,
these paint balloons
on the level
and I have a enemy
that's in the scene.
So to give the enemy the same
fighting ability by picking
up the paint balloons
and throw at me,
I'm going to give the
same fight component.
And to make this a fair game,
I'm going to give the same
health level of 2 rather
than using the default
value of 1.
Now, I think my level
is set up pretty good.
Let's run it and check it
out, the new implementation.
So the drones are going
to be dropping randomly
the paint balloons
and the paintball
fighter will start.
So looks like all the
elements are all there.
So in Xcode 8, it's very easy to
implement the level of the game
and connect all these
gameplay logics fairly quickly.
Because I'm using
SpriteKit and GameplayKit,
my game will automatically
run on all Apple platforms.
Thank you.
Now, back to Andreas.
[ Applause ]
>> Thank you, Norman.
All right, so just quickly
review the most important points
we talked about.
There are now four Apple
OS platforms, each of them
with their own App Store that
you can bring your ideas to.
And today we added a large
variety of new extension points
that allow you to hook
even deeper into our OS's.
Perhaps most importantly,
we recommend
that you consider creating
an iMessage App and also
that you integrate
your apps with SiriKit.
But these are just two
of the many new APIs we
are announcing today.
And support for all of
them will be provided
by a new version
of our Xcode IDE.
Xcode 8 is going to run on
Mac OS El Capitan and Sierra.
Now, of course, it
also has support
for developing with Swift 3.
Now, all these technologies
are available for download
from the WWDC Attendee
Portal today,
so you can get early access and
use the time later in the year
when we ship out products to
get ready for all launches,
create even more powerful and
unique apps for your users.
Also, go and check out the
new Swift Playgrounds app,
which we're including in
the iOS X Developer Preview.
I think you're going to
have a ton of fun with it
and perhaps you'll consider
creating additional content
for your kids to start
learning how to program Swift.
Now, there are many
opportunities here
at the conference for you to
learn more about everything
that we announced today.
There's more than 100
sessions you can attend
and even more labs.
You can meet every engineer
you see on site one on one.
They are here to answer
you specific questions.
So I hope you enjoyed the
session and I'll see you
around later this week.
[ Applause ]