[ Music ]
>> Hello, developers.
What a great venue.
This is really great.
Thanks for coming today.
It's been a long day, but we've
got some really great stuff
for you.
So I want to welcome you
to the 15th Apple
Design Award Ceremony.
And we've got a ton of
great winners this evening.
And we'd like to, of course,
recognize their great work.
The Apple Design Awards are all
about recognizing great work
by people in this community.
And this is the moment when many
of you -- well, many of you --
some of you get to take home one
of the Apple Design
Award Trophies,
which everyone wants one.
And so we'll see who
gets one tonight.
But to start things off, I
just want to set a little bit
of context for the apps that
are going to win tonight.
The App Store opened
eight years ago.
In fact, next month it'll
be exactly eight years old.
And it was on July 10th of 2008.
And in those eight
years, apps took off.
Right? They've taken off.
And today, we heard 2
million apps on the App Store.
But if we just go
back for a moment
to those first days,
it was pretty crazy.
I mean, it all started off
with the iPhone, right?
And we all remember
the first TV ads.
They were 30-second slots.
And in those 30-second
slots, you had five
or six apps that were featured.
And so each app had five
seconds to audition with you,
the customer -- with
you, the audience.
And to make an impression
in five seconds is
a pretty big deal.
But what happened in those ads
was people would watch the ads
and they would stop
everything that they were doing
and they would pay attention to
the app that was being shown.
And within five seconds,
they would have decided
whether it mattered to them
and if they were going to go
and download it or buy it.
And I think that's
pretty impressive.
And those apps -- basically, it
was those TV ads and those apps
that created the phrase,
"There's an app for that."
And that phrase was born.
And it was during
that time way early
on that we saw enormous
creativity.
I mean, we didn't have
this thing before.
iPhone was out.
We had this SDK.
We didn't have that before.
And we saw enormous creativity.
We saw great games,
really useful
and very valuable utilities,
some pretty incredible
augmented reality,
and lots of other great stuff,
much of which was
really groundbreaking.
And then, two years later,
the iPad was introduced.
And it was introduced
not far from here
at the Yerba Buena
Center of the Arts.
And I remember that day.
It was an incredible day.
But when the iPad
arrived in 2010,
it brought a whole
new wave of apps.
And these were apps that
stopped us in our tracks.
I mean these were apps that,
when we first saw them,
they caused us to
pause and to be amazed
at what could be
done on this device.
And then we had universal
apps coming
and bringing functionality
from iPad back to iPhone,
and the experience of all
of the apps got better.
And all of these apps early on
changed the way that we taught.
They changed the way that
people learned with iPad.
They changed the way that we
shared, that we connected,
that we worked, and that
we spent our day getting
things done.
These were transformational
apps.
And then more recently,
Apple Watch was introduced,
and Apple TV.
And with each of these, we
saw a new wave of apps coming.
And so now, as you've
heard several times today,
we've got four platforms
for you.
And this is amazing.
I mean, for me, being
at Apple 16 years,
I remember when it
was just the Mac
and there was some
great work going on.
And then everything took
off, and now the Mac is part
of that whole ecosystem.
And there's a tremendous
opportunity for you
with these four platforms.
And we're starting to see
some really great work
from developers on
these four platforms,
and a few of those will
be honored here tonight.
Now, tonight's winners
have created apps that are,
once again, that set a
benchmark for excellence.
And they set a benchmark
for excellence in usability,
excellence in design, excellent
innovation, and excellence
in technology adoption.
And if you've been part of
the Apple Design Awards before
or ever heard me speak, you know
that that's not all
there is to a great app.
There's even more that we
look for in winning apps.
We're always looking for
whether the app is compelling
and leaves a great
first impression.
We're always looking for
whether an app is engaging,
meaning it draws you
in and keeps you there,
and then gets you coming
back again and again.
That's a big challenge for apps.
We look for apps that are
enabling, that allow you
to do things you
could never do before.
We're looking for
state-of-the-art apps of course.
accessible apps.
We're looking for
localized apps.
Because accessible and
localized apps mean
that those apps are available
to an even wider audience
than they were prior to being
accessible and localized.
And so there's a lot
of stuff that we look
for in winning apps, and these
are just some of the things
that we watch for
in winning apps.
So let's get started.
Let's start with apps that
were written by students.
So you've heard today that we
had 350 scholarship winners this
year at WWDC, which
is a record number.
And these folks, these
students, had to submit an app.
As part of the scholarship
process,
they had to submit an app that
was either written explicitly
for the scholarship
selection process,
or they could just
tell us about an app
that they had already
developed and put on --
that was already
on the App Store.
And we looked through
all these apps
and we found some
pretty cool stuff.
So tonight we want to
award two student winners.
And the first is Linum by
Joaquin Vila from Mexico.
[ Applause ]
>> Thanks so much.
>> You're welcome.
[ Music ]
All right, so Joaquin
started developing this app
after he had applied for a
job at a local game developer,
and that hadn't worked out.
And he decided after
that that, like,
he could just do
this on his own.
He didn't need to work
for no other developer.
So he decided to write his own
app, get it on the App Store.
And I'd like to show
you this app.
And before I do, I just wanted
to say Joaquin was a 2015
Scholarship Winner last year
at WWDC, so probably
learned a lot
about what you used
in the app last year.
And he's also super active in
the local developer community
in many of the meetups
in his hometown.
All right, so I'm just going to
show you this on this screen.
So what you're seeing here
is Linum is a puzzle game
where the goal is
to complete levels
in the fewest moves possible.
And what you're trying to do is
take these line nodes and lines
and pivot them around to connect
with nodes to solve the puzzles.
And as the number
of nodes increases,
complex puzzles challenge
even the best players.
And the beauty of Linum
is its simplicity.
It's got a clean UI and
a simple set of rules.
And with a smart
implementation of touch
and approachable
progression system,
terrific overall presentation
and use of Apple technologies,
Linum is without doubt an
Apple Design Award Winner
for a student.
So, congratulations.
[ Applause ]
All right.
And our second student
winner tonight is Dividr
by Josh Deichmann, Patrick
Pistor, and Erik Lydick.
[ Applause ]
Congratulations.
[ Music ]
So I guess just one of
you are here today, yeah?
>> Yeah.
>> No problem.
There's three guys.
So all three of these guys, one
of whom is here, are students
at the Rochester
Institute of Technology
in Northern New York State.
And at RIT, they went to an iOS
development challenge earlier
this year.
And it was at that event
that they started
working on this game.
And Josh is the programmer.
Is it Josh?
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah, Josh is the programmer.
Patrick is the designer.
And Erik is the guy who created
the soundtrack for the game
but also kind of kept you
guys on track, you know,
in terms of development.
So let me just show you
this game for a minute.
So Dividr is this fun and
addicting 2D arcade game.
And it makes use of 3D
touch of variant pressure
to move the control
squares in and out depending
on the pressure that
you apply to the screen.
So the more pressure you
apply, the further out they go.
The lighter on you are,
the closer in they go.
And you're basically avoiding
these obstacles on screen.
It's simple and compelling,
written entirely
in Swift, supports Game Center.
And it was, without a
doubt, a great choice
for an Apple Design
Award this evening.
Congratulations.
[ Applause ]
This side.
All right.
So those are our 2 winning
apps developed by students.
Pretty great stuff.
And there were lots more.
But, you know, we've got
to draw the line somewhere.
Not everybody can win.
All right, now let's move on
to your main winners tonight.
We have 10 winners this
year, and 10 winners
which are all super compelling.
They're all incredibly
well-designed.
They're all super
state-of-the-art.
And they're all optimized
for the devices
that they were created
for and for the use cases
that customers will
face with them.
And so let's begin.
The first Apple Design
Award Winner
for 2016 is Frame.io
by Frame.io, Inc.
from New York City.
[ Applause ]
[ Music ]
Congratulations.
Great job, guys.
Great to meet you.
[ Music ]
All right, so Frame.io is a
video collaboration platform
for teens working
together on film or video.
And it lets these teens easily
share files, give feedback,
review clips, approve media,
and do a whole ton of stuff
in that creative pro workflow.
And it turns out that it's
really hard to do this right.
And Frame.io nails it
by filling a big gap
in the creator pro workflow by
solving this complicated task.
And to give you a better
idea of how this app works,
I'd like to ask Michael
to demo it to us now.
>> Thank you, John.
So this is a typical
project in Frame.io.
Now it's really media-centric,
so you can see all the media
in the lower half of the view.
Now -- whoops.
So basically what they've
done here is they've made a
UICollectionViewFlowLayout
with UIKit dynamics,
and that really makes
this view come alive.
Now at the top, you can see
all the project participants.
Now this is a really fun
and interactive animation.
And that's really cool,
and I can do it slow.
There we go.
And that's using core animation
with custom curves
and key frames.
That opens up to a table
list view where I can swipe
to remove someone from a project
or leave the project myself.
Now the media player is
really key to Frame.io.
And so what they've done here
is they've implemented 3D touch,
and they've done this in a
number of different ways.
The first one is a feature
they call Touch Scrub.
So on this clip of this mountain
-- all I'm going to do is scrub
across this clip very lightly.
And you can see I
get an overview
of the clip really quickly.
Now the other thing that they've
done is they've gone deeper
and implemented peak and pop.
So on this clip, I'm
going to push gently.
That peaks in.
And now watch this.
When I pop, it goes
to the same frame
into a new view --
the Comment View.
Pretty cool stuff.
Now the Comment View is
where all the project
participants come in
and actually collaborate.
All these comments
are time-synchronized.
So when I touch something,
it actually goes to the frame
where the comment was made.
You'll also notice that all
the commenter's pictures turn
to a Play button.
So for example, here you
can see that Play button.
If I touch the Play
button, it's a feature
that they call Comment Replay
where it will start
playing two seconds before
and two seconds after.
And then where the comment
is, the comment flashes
and the phone will vibrate.
One more time.
And here's the comment.
That's where it is.
So I'm going to let this video
play out just a little bit
because I know that there's
something wrong in here --
and there's a lion
in my surf video.
You know, like, really?
So I'm going to put my
comment in, but I'm also going
to go ahead and annotate
and send that comment along.
So this app is incredible.
It's written entirely in Swift.
It's using the latest tools.
It's using multiple storyboards,
storyboard references,
auto layout, size classes.
Did I mention it
was done in Swift?
Did I mention that this
is their first iOS app?
This is a really great app.
Congratulations to the team.
Back to you, John.
[ Applause ]
>> Yeah, so Frame.io
is a great app.
We love this app.
Hitting the wrong button here,
that's why we're
messing up here.
Apologies.
We love this app.
Congratulations, guys.
You've solved a really big
problem in a very elegant way.
[ Applause ]
All right, our second
winner tonight is a game.
And it is Chameleon Run by
Jan Ilavsky and published
by Noodlecake Studios
from Canada.
[ Applause ]
>> Thank you.
[ Music ]
>> It's just great to
watch some of these photos
to see people's studios.
I mean, we were amazed as we
looked through some of the shots
from the winners tonight.
The places in which you
work are super creative.
And we couldn't get
enough of this game.
With a great soundtrack, fun
sound effects, super intuitive
and natural controls
and great performance,
Chameleon Run is an
Apple Design Award Winner
that you are not going
to want to put down.
And to show you this game, I'd
like to ask Allan and Mark.
>> Great. So thank you, John.
Hello, everyone.
Chameleon Run is
a super fast-paced
and very challenging auto-runner
with a twist that's
based on color.
And it has a really
stunning visual presentation
which we'd like to show you now.
My colleague, Mark,
is joining us.
He's going to play while I
tell you about this game.
So the objective of
Chameleon Run is to make it
through the level in
the best possible time.
And Mark is jumping from
platform to platform.
But if you notice, when he lands
on a platform, sometimes he has
to switch the character's color
to match the platform
he's landing on.
And that becomes
very challenging
as you make your way
through this game.
OK, so that was a
very easy level.
Let's do it one more time
because I want to point
out a couple more
things on this level,
especially the rendering
effects.
That was something that we
really loved about this game.
If you take a look at the
depth of field with the objects
in the background, the
shock waves coming off
of the character, and
also the smoke trails
and just the particle effect.
We thought that all of that
really added something visually
to this game.
But, OK, so we did
very well there.
That was an easy level.
And now Mark is going to go
for something much,
much more difficult.
Go all the way.
All right, here we go.
Level 15, The End is Near.
And let me tell you a little bit
about why we chose this game.
So first of all, as I said,
we love the visual style
and just the vibrancy of
the colors in this game.
And it was so clear that so
much care and iteration went
into the construction
of the levels
and just fine-tuning
this content.
Then the second thing --
Mark is doing very well.
All right.
Nice.
[ Applause ]
Do it again.
Go for it.
So the second thing
is the replayability.
Yeah, OK, that's me playing
now -- most of the time.
So the replayability in this
game is just phenomenal.
Most of these levels have
in effect a high road
and a low road that
you can take.
You sort of can go up and down
as you're progressing
through the level.
But the game really
encourages you to go back
and play the levels
over and over again.
Maybe the first time through
you're going for time.
But then it unlocks
different objectives
to collect all the crystals or
to go entirely through the level
without switching your color,
which imagine how difficult
that would be on a level
like the one we just saw.
And the third thing about this
game is that this is a game
that is great on
your iPhone and iPad,
but it is awesome
on your Apple TV.
We love how this plays
with the Siri Remote.
That's what Mark is using now.
It also plays great
with an MFi controller.
And it's just one of these
games that is just fantastic
when you see it on the big
screen in your living room.
So that's Chameleon Run.
It supports Game Center.
It's localized in 8 languages,
and it's a premium title.
Just pay once and play.
So, congratulations.
Back to you, John.
[ Applause ]
>> Thanks, Allan.
Thanks, Mark.
That's Chameleon Run --
a super engaging game
that you'll be playing
again and again.
All right, our next winner
is Auxy Music Creation
by Auxy from Sweden.
[ Applause ]
[ Music ]
Auxy Music Creation is an
audio creation app for iPad.
And the Auxy team realized
that electronic music was going
mainstream, and so they sat down
and started to develop this app
that allowed electronic fans
to create some of their own
tracks on an iOS device.
And this is a super
compelling app
with a clean minimalist style.
And honestly inside of this
app, it's almost impossible
to create something that
doesn't sound great.
No matter what you tap
on, you get great results.
So I'd like to ask Michael
again to show us this app.
>> Great. Thank you, John.
So the first thing
that we really loved
about Auxy was the really subtle
and unobtrusive onboarding.
Now I'm not locked
out from the app.
I can go anywhere I want,
but we'll follow the trail
and see where it leads us.
So I'll double-tap to start
creating my first loops
and drums.
I'll start with some bass drum.
That's great.
So now it told me that
I can move some notes
around by dragging,
which is really handy
because I just missed that one.
So we'll do some high hat.
And notice how quick and
how performant the UI is.
It's really cool.
OK, I'm going to add some
tom-toms on the off beats.
That actually sounds more like
a kettle drum than a tom-tom,
and that's great because the
onboarding is telling me how
to change my kit.
So let's see if I can find
something a little hipper.
Not that. Not that.
70's disco -- that's
what I'm looking for.
OK. So now what do we
need for 70's disco?
We need some disco base, right?
So let's add another loop.
Great. So the UI is really
responsive because they built
on top of UIKit, and that
is built on top of Metal.
They also went ahead
and implemented Grand
Central Dispatch.
That really helps
with the performance.
I'm going to add
one more loop here.
[ Music ]
Now I can do a lot with this.
But what I'm going to do is
I'm going to open up something
that I already have created.
And then now we can hear how
these guys have gone ahead
and created a really,
really powerful synth
engine on the iPad.
So let's listen to the drums.
OK, the drums really -- they
have a lot of character.
There's a nice reverb
tail in there.
Let's add some bass.
It's a really fat bass.
Let's add some synth.
Really rich, analog-sounding
synth.
I'm going to play around
with this for a little while.
[ Music ]
That's not bad.
I'm going to take the Doodle
Patch and I'm going to mess
around with it a little bit.
I'm going to bring up my
synth controls and I'm going
to change the character
of my synth
and make it more aggressive.
So we're going to turn down
our attack and we're going
to open up the filter.
Nice and aggressive -- that's
what I was looking for.
I'm going to use Multi-Touch
to bring it on home.
[ Music ]
Seriously, I could do
this all night long.
Now this is really great stuff.
All these guys.
[ Applause ]
The thing that we
loved that we loved
about Auxy is they
took Apple technology
and they implemented
it in such a way
that customers could have fun
and they could be creative
without that technology
getting in the way.
Really great stuff.
Love this app.
Congratulations.
Back to you, John.
[ Applause ]
>> That's pretty cool.
Thank you.
I was just talking for a moment
here how big the team is,
and it's three people
that created this.
So here's an app --
Auxy Music Creation.
More than 4,000 5-star
reviews on the App Store,
and it's exclusive to iPad.
All right, our fourth
winner is an app
that helps you to
form good habits.
Congratulations to Streaks
by Zervaas Enterprises
from Australia.
[ Applause ]
[ Music ]
Good job.
>> Thank you.
>> Yeah.
[ Music ]
So, Streaks is a to-do list
that helps you form good
habits and change behavior.
And Streaks has a simple
and straightforward UI,
and it's got an excellent
implementation on Apple Watch --
probably the best Apple
Watch app available today.
And we'd like to show
you Streaks right now.
TC?
>> Thanks, John.
So trying to form good
habits is difficult.
The last thing you want is
an app that is complicated
to set up, uninspiring to use,
and pretty much itself a
reason for procrastination.
So here are five of
the possible six tasks
that I've set up for myself.
And you can see on the top
right "Practice cello".
So I miss playing the
cello professionally,
but I just haven't
been practicing.
I'm using Streaks to help get me
back to it, to help me remember
to practice regularly because
I have a concert coming up.
And I've been saying
that for a few years now.
[ Laughter ]
So to see how I've been doing,
I can just tap on the Task icon
for the calendar view here.
I can also peak and pop onto it.
And you can see June
was pretty good.
But if I was to reveal to
you May -- not so good.
So the crosses is where,
for whatever reason,
I've decided not to practice.
Coming back here
and tapping again,
this is a summary
of how I've done.
And you can see that
I'm currently
on a streak of 15 days.
Now we're back here.
To mark a task complete,
all I do is to tap and hold.
And there you go.
It's like I've just finished
practicing for today.
Now when I was outside earlier,
I was reading the iOS 10
API disk documentation.
So I'm going to go and check
"Read the book" as
complete as well.
Now Streaks is also
on Apple Watch.
And it has Watch complications
right onto your Watch face,
including one that is
really cleverly designed.
It's based on a dotted
design which looks just
like the iPhone app so that
you can tell from just looking
at how the dots are arranged
and which ones are
lit how you're doing
with your task for that day.
Streaks uses Watch connectivity
extensively, so my Apple Watch
and iPhone are always in sync.
Now Streaks is also considerate,
and I'll show you what I mean,
especially in the way it
handles notifications.
For instance, when it comes
to automatic time and my cat,
Auzuki, Streaks knows that
I play with her every day
when I come home from
work immediately,
otherwise she gets quite cranky.
And nobody wants a cranky cat.
So it knows to remind me
at the same time each day
but 30 minutes in advance of
that so that I can continue
that streak and have
a happy cat.
All right?
And it also looks at
HealthKit to try and figure
out when it is I
typically go to bed
so that it doesn't send me a
reminder too late into my day.
For when things are
going really well,
you get encouragement as well.
And in addition to that, Streaks
will suggest perhaps a higher
goal so that you achieve
an overall greater result.
Now, conversely, if you've
been missing a few tasks,
it will suggest an
easier-to-achieve goal
so you don't end up giving up.
OK, so Streaks is
a 5-star rated app.
It's exclusive to iOS and Watch,
and it was developed
using Swift.
Bad habits form automatically.
Streaks helps us come
up with good ones.
I'm more confident than ever
that I'll be playing my
cello soon in a concert,
or to read many books, and
have a really happy cat.
Thank you.
[ Applause ]
>> So that's Streaks.
We picked this app as a
winner for its simplicity,
the great visual design, and
the excellent implementation
on Apple Watch.
They're localized into 25
languages and they're exclusive
to iPhone, Apple Watch, and
Apple TV as TC just mentioned.
All right, our next
winner is, again, a game.
Lara Croft by Square Enix.
[ Applause ]
[ Music ]
So Lara Croft Go
captures the spirit
of this classic franchise,
and then reimagines it
into this classy new app with an
innovative new look and turns it
into this great adventure game.
This is a great example of
a large developer working
with a small studio
within their organization
to give them the task
of creating something
that's really well-executed
down to the smallest detail.
These guys have done
a tremendous job
with this huge franchise.
These folks are based
out of Montreal, Canada.
Right? And it's great --
you've done a tremendous job.
Now to show you this game,
I'd like to ask Allan
to give a demo.
>> Great. Thank you, John.
So Lara Croft Go is a turn-based
puzzle adventure game that's set
in the ruins of an
ancient civilization.
And what we loved about this
game is how it took so many
of the elements of the
Lara Croft franchise --
things like the archeological
exploration, and the adventure,
and solving puzzles and avoiding
traps, and Lara herself --
and reimagined all those things
into a puzzle game
that's perfect for mobile
and beautifully designed
for touch.
So I'd like to show you it here.
I'm coming into a level
here that's onboarding me
into a new game mechanic
that has to do
with these rolling boulders.
But actually, before
I even do that,
just take this in for a moment.
I mean, check out the
stylized rendering.
I hope you can all hear the
ambient soundtrack here.
It's just beautiful.
And we really love
things like the attention
to detail in the levels.
And it has a really
unobtrusive UI.
There's no virtual joypad
here to move Lara around.
To move Lara to the next space,
I just swipe and she moves.
But, OK, so let's start
looking through this level here.
Obviously there's this
boulder, and I have a feeling
that if I step on
the trap -- yeah.
OK. So, mental note, don't
step under falling boulders.
But we can put that knowledge
to work a little bit later.
Isn't it cool how she kind
of hangs off the ledge there?
All right, but I'm going
forward a little further here.
Here's another one.
I'm going to get it going,
but then I'll take a step back
and let it roll past me.
OK, so I'm safe.
And I come down now into
the next part of the stage.
All right.
So now in this part, I'm
going to pick up the spear.
But I'm not going
to use that yet.
What I'm going to do --
this lizard has woken up
and I'm going to step back
and let him step on the trap.
Bam! OK, no more lizard.
So now let's go forward.
And this next one wakes up.
OK, now the game mechanic here
is that as I move once space,
the lizard will move one space.
And it'll follow me through
whatever path I take.
So I'm going to climb
up the wall here
and go a particular way to get
him right where I want him.
Bam! It never gets old.
All right.
And I'm going to
dispatch the snake.
Great. And that finishes
out this particular
stage of this level.
And, really, this is just
a taste of this game.
There's over a hundred
of these different scenes
with incredible detail.
And it's just hats off to
you guys for this creation.
It's really beautiful.
The game supports
Game Center and iCloud
to synchronize its progress
across all of your devices.
It's localized in 11
different languages.
And it's a premium title with
a couple of in-app purchases --
one to provide you solutions
to puzzles if you get stuck,
and the other to
customize the character.
So, again, hats off to you guys.
Congratulations.
[ Applause ]
>> So that's Lara Croft Go.
It's tuned for iOS and has more
than 5,000 5-star
ratings on the App Store.
Tremendous work.
All right, our next winner is
3D4Medical Complete Anatomy
from Ireland.
[ Applause ]
Congrats.
>> Thank you.
>> Great job.
[ Music ]
This is a groundbreaking
3D anatomical platform
for medical students,
medical professionals,
and lifelong learners.
And we love this app for how
it's disrupting traditional ways
of teaching anatomy.
For example, medical
professionals will use this app
as a tool to help patients
understand what's going
on with an injury or
an upcoming procedure.
And that understanding actually
helps people heal better
and more quickly.
And I'd like to ask
my colleague, Chris,
to show this to you now.
>> This was an app that
completely blew us away
with its attention to detail,
graphics and animations,
and most importantly what
it allowed users to do.
We love the iconography
throughout that.
Check out along the bottom menu.
The icons are consistent
and representative
of what they control.
I'm going to turn
some of these layers
on so you can get an
idea of what's in here.
The app has over 6,200
structures, so it's deep
without being overwhelming.
The content is progressively
displayed as you need it.
Just a tremendous
amount of content.
But I'm going to turn
these layers off for now
and move into the bone.
Notice the incredible
shading and textures.
They're the result of
high-resolution scans
and artist interpretations.
The team has a skeleton on
staff named Hank, a cadaver,
and a medical team
that they reference
to get things just right.
We love it when a team
goes that extra mile
to make things particularly
beautiful.
If at any point in the app
you see something that's
interesting, you can just tap
on it to learn a bit more.
Are there any Warriors
fans in the audience?
[ Cheering ]
This is the ligament that nearly
cost the Warriors their season
when Steph went out with that
knee injury a couple weeks back.
Now I'm going to
turn on some muscle
so we can see some movement.
I can select on a muscle group
and I can see how that works.
I can adjust this
motion in real time,
rotate, and see things in 3D.
One of the reasons
we chose this app is
because it leveraged the
performance of iPad Pro.
With the new CPU and GPU,
it allowed double the graphics
resolution of previous versions.
Again, check out the
texture on that muscle.
Just incredibly realistic.
Now we could spend hours just
exploring content in this app,
but 3D4Medical wanted
to allow users
to create and share content.
So at any point in the
app, I can start recording.
So I'm going to do that now.
So I'm now recording audio
and what's on the screen.
I can use this --
if I was a teacher,
I could create a
lesson for a student.
Or if I was a physician, I
could record a common procedure
to share with my patients.
For the baseball fans, what I'm
doing here is I'm using Apple
Pencil to pull back the
layers of the muscle
to show the ligaments that
were repaired during Tommy
John's surgery.
Imagine a physician
sharing something like this
with a patient before
a procedure.
I can then save the
recording for my own use.
Or if I choose, I can share it
with the 3D4Medical Community.
We love it when a developer
tackles a unique problem
in a new way.
This is a team that
looked at human anatomy
and what they could do with iPad
and created a world-class
education tool.
Congratulations, guys.
Back to you, John.
[ Applause ]
>> 3D4Medical Complete Anatomy.
We picked this out for its
incredible performance,
its high-fidelity models,
the attention to detail,
and the uncluttered UI.
It's exclusive to
iPad Pro right now,
but it's coming to
Mac this summer.
And it's unbelievable.
All right, our seventh
winner is really beautiful.
It is INKS by State of
Play Games from London.
[ Applause ]
Congratulations.
>> Thank you.
[ Music ]
>> So INKS is from the makers
of Lumino City based in the UK.
And after extensive research at
their local pub, they decided
to create a new generation
of pinball.
And if you think about it, INKS.
is sort of a cross between
paintball and pinball
with an artistic flare.
And you've got to see this.
So for the demo, I
decided I'd ask Mike,
the evangelism resident pinball
expert, to show this to you now.
>> Thanks, John.
So right from the
Welcome Screen,
you get to enjoy the
beautifully stunning
and highly realistic INKS.
The way they blend together the
colors here are really gorgeous.
Now as I hit the
pinball through,
you can see how it traces
those colors one into the other
and draws it onto the paper.
It's really pretty awesome.
All right, let's play a game.
Now INKS features
five different levels,
each of which has 24 different
boards, each with its own set
of obstacles, challenges,
and increasing complexity.
As John said, I'm kind
of a pinball wizard.
So I'll start with one of
the more advanced ones,
but not so advanced
that you guys feel bad
about your pinball skills.
Now check out each
of these boards.
They're each custom designed,
obviously handcrafted
with a lot of thought and care.
They're their own
beautiful compositions
on their own before
you even start to play.
And check out the gold, and
silver, and bronze pinballs.
These show you how well you've
done in each of these levels.
Now bronze is not good enough,
so let me show you
guys how it's done.
[ Laughter ]
There must be a problem
with this iPad.
[ Laughter ]
All right, let me redeem myself.
Oh, man. OK, this was a
lot easier in rehearsals
when I didn't have
5,000 people watching.
All right, so I'm going to go
to one of the easier levels.
[ Laughter ]
And just to show you guys
this, too, INKS offers hours
of gameplay for more beginner
players -- of which I am not.
All right, let's try this.
Bam! That's how I do!
[ Laughter ]
All right.
So what I want to show you
guys is some of the levels
that really demonstrate
the highly realistic INKS
that I was talking
about earlier.
So there's that big color
swatch in the center.
And each time you hit one, it
explodes and reacts to force
and angle in its own unique way.
And check out how the
colors continue to blend
into each other and
darken as they go.
The team spent a lot of
time studying water colors,
the physics of it, the
dynamics, how it dries
into the paper and blends.
It's really gorgeous.
And I'll show you just
one more level here
that just shows off how,
even though this is a
completely new take on pinball,
they still respected a lot of
the sound effects, and the feel
of the bumpers, and habitrails,
and drop targets,
and the flippers.
I mean, it's really,
really amazing.
And I'm probably not going to
have time to finish this one.
I'll just let it go
down the drain there.
But I think this really
demonstrates how you can take a
traditional game mechanic
and with enough thought,
attention to detail and
care, create something
which is completely
fresh and unique.
Brilliant job.
Thanks. Back to you.
[ Applause ]
>> Thanks, Mike.
So it's obvious that we picked
this game as a winner tonight
because it's really
well-designed.
It's rich and unique.
It's available in
five languages,
and it's exclusive to iOS.
And it's also really
interesting to note that a lot
of the conceptualization and the
artistry was done on an iPad Pro
with Apple Pencil by the team.
So they used some other tools,
too, to come up with this.
So that's INKS.
Our eighth winner today
-- a fitness app --
is Zova Personal Trainer by
ZOVA Group from Australia.
[ Applause ]
Congrats, guys.
Congratulations.
Good job. Well done.
Good job.
>> Thanks.
[ Music ]
>> So Zova is a fitness
training app
that helps people stay
active using motivation
and great HD videos that
look awesome on Apple TV.
And we loved it because
it's thoughtful,
and in so many ways
they took little things
and considered them deeply.
And it's really great
on Apple TV.
In fact, we like this app so
much that we took it with us
on the roadshow this fall --
the Apple TV Tech Talks --
and we used it as one
of the reference apps
in our design sessions.
And we'd like to
show it to you now.
So, TC?
>> Thanks again, John.
Zova is a fitness app
that provides short,
achievable, daily exercises.
Now this team here
they've been early adopters
of Apple technologies from day
1 with their initial release
of the app and HealthKit
support,
to then Apple Watch support, and
most recently Apple TV support.
But they don't just
do it gratuitously.
They only deliver on
unique experiences conducive
to each platform
that feels natural
as if it always meant
to be that.
And today, we'd like to
talk about the Apple TV app.
So with Apple TV, they didn't
just upsize the content.
They took the Apple TV
concept to heart and thought
about the whole medium of TV.
TV is a major part of our lives.
It's when we gather together to
enjoy content and experiences.
Now workout apps don't have to
be lonesome activities anymore.
With the communal experiences
afforded by Apple TV,
Zova had to think about the kind
of content that they can create.
This collection here called
Move Together is where you team
up with your friend and
actually workout together
and get fit together.
But Zova didn't just stop
at rethinking content.
They also wanted to take full
advantage of the Siri Remote.
As you will see me
navigating through this, it is,
as you would expect, very
easy to find content.
And focusing on elements
is easy, too.
Let's go into this workout here.
So, here, you get
a brief description
of what this workout is about.
And also, if you have
a look at the bottom,
these are video previews
of exactly what the
exercises entail.
That way, you know what
you're really in for.
But where the implementation
of Siri Remote really comes
into its own is when you're
actually inside of a workout.
So let's try one of these.
Each workout starts with a
preview, so you're reminded
of exactly what the exercise is.
Now I've just pressed the
Pause button, and it responds
as you would expect because
you will get interrupted
when you're trying to exercise.
That's just the way it is.
When you resume the pause,
it will give you a countdown
so that you can actually
ready yourself instead
of just jumping straight
into it.
But where it gets really
interesting is I'm now pressing
and holding onto the Pause
button, and instead I'm provided
with a freeze frame so that
I can look more closely
at the details on the screen --
perhaps the exact
posture of the instructor.
Now this is possible and is
beyond the standard controls
because Zova has implemented
a custom AVPlayerLayer.
Similarly, if I was
to swipe left,
I can restart an
exercise very quickly.
Or, if I was to swipe
to the right,
you can see I can easily skip.
Now you may have noticed
references earlier
to Apple Watch.
This is really neat.
What's happening here is
it's taking my heartrate
from my Watch.
And through HealthKit and
my iPhone, it is overlaying
that onto the live
video stream here.
So that's my heartrate
you're looking at.
Let's move along then.
At the end of each workout, you
have an opportunity to, I guess,
log your feedback as
to how you've done.
And this is a really fun
use of the Siri Remote.
You can either give it a big
thumbs-up for it has gone well,
or if it's gone less well --
and in my case, I tend to
quiver my lips a little, too.
So there you go.
[ Laughter ]
We really like Zova's
reimagination of content
for the lounge and living
room, and the extensive use
of the features of
the Apple Siri Remote
so that you have a true
and unique Apple TV
experience in your lounge room.
Built using Swift, Zova
is exclusive to iOS,
Watch OS, and Apple TV.
Congratulations to
the team at ZOVA.
And back to you, John.
[ Applause ]
>> All right, that's Zova.
The next winner this
afternoon is Ulysses
by the Soulmen from Germany.
[ Applause ]
[ Music ]
So Ulysses is a powerful
text editor for writers
of all kinds -- journalists,
bloggers, you name it.
And it's designed specifically
to cover all aspects
of the writing process.
And we picked it as a winner
because it's a tool
that's optimized
for writing without distraction.
The entire UI of the
operating system goes away
and you're just working
with your words.
And the execution of
this app is so great.
It allows you to work
on any of our devices.
You can choose to start on
the Mac, then move to iPad,
then move to iPhone,
and move back.
And you get that
distraction-free experience
on any of those devices.
And to show this app to you, I'd
like to turn it over to Michael.
>> Thank you, John.
So Ulysses is a focused
and distraction-free
writing environment.
It has the power of
classic word processers
with flexible organization
and management tools.
Now it's a super clean writing
experience and it has features
to help you through the task.
So the first thing, for example,
is I can highlight
the current line.
That should look familiar.
We can also show
paragraph numbers.
Now Ulysses is based
on Markdown.
And what Markdown is --
it's a markup language
that uses plain text
and special characters
to set semantics.
So, for example, here you
can see that in this copy
of the Apple TV human
interface guidelines
that navigation has
two hash marks,
and that is a second-level
header.
By the way, this tear-off menu
is from their use of AppKit.
Now Ulysses also presents images
and URLs in a user-friendly
and vey distraction-free way.
Now Ulysses is really
customizable.
For me, for example, I
like working at night.
I get creative after
dark, so I like Dark Mode.
If Dark Mode doesn't
work for you,
there are customizable themes,
or you can download themes
from the Ulysses User Community.
Now Markdown is an open
standard, so they also ship
with a number of different
markdown definitions,
or you can create your own.
Both custom markdown definitions
and custom themes are all
synchronized using iCloud.
OK. Now this is a modern,
single-window, multicolumn app.
So if you take a look all
the way on the left side,
that's my library column.
And in my library column,
that's where I manage
all of my writing.
For example, here I have a
group of public domain books.
I also have filters.
Now a filter is sort
of a persistent search.
So here, for example, I'm
searching for the word "Ishmael"
or the name "Ishmael".
And all of the occurrences
come up, most of them
from the book "Moby Dick".
And I can also change the icon
to something a little
bit more appropriate.
I can also do ad hoc searches.
So, for example, I know that
there is a single occurrence
of the word "galleon"
in all of these books.
And if I take a look
at the search base using
the statistics feature,
I can see that I just searched
through about 1.3 million words,
most of those written
by James Joyce.
And that's thanks to their
implementation of Spotlight
and Grand Central Dispatch.
Okie dokie.
So let's go back here.
Let's kill this.
Let's go back to
our Apple TV HIG.
All right.
Now Ulysses is
delivery-agnostic,
so it doesn't matter where
you're going to deliver from.
You can preview in a number
of different formats
powered by TextKit, PDFKit.
It can even publish
directly to Medium.
But one of the things
that they've done is
they've allowed you
to make your own CSS files
to style the preview
exactly the way you need it.
So, for example, here
I have an HTML preview
and I happen to have
an Apple CSS.
And I can apply that
to my preview, like so.
And you can see how the
Apple TV HIG would look
on an Apple website.
All right.
Now as John mentioned, Ulysses
is available on OS X and iOS,
eventually Mac OS I hope.
It implements Handoff.
It's available in 7 languages.
We love this app.
We use this app at Apple.
We're so happy and so proud
that you guys have created
this and won an ADA.
So, congratulations.
Back to you, John.
[ Applause ]
>> So, as Michael said
-- thank you, Michael.
As Michael said, Ulysses is
a great example of an app
that takes advantage of iOS and
OS X, Handoff, iCloud and more
to deliver an optimized
experience
on each of these platforms.
We talked about this new
opportunity of four platforms,
and this is an app
that does a great job
of heading in that direction.
Congratulations.
All right, our last
winner today is an app
that is incredibly
state-of-the-art
and incredibly accessible.
It is djay Pro by
Algoriddim from Germany.
[ Applause ]
You've been here before.
You've been here before, sir.
Good. Congratulations.
[ Music ]
All right, so djay Pro is one
of the first professional-grade
apps to fully leverage the audio
and video capabilities
of the new iPad Pro.
And these guys already won an
Apple Design Award in 2011,
but they have done
so much since then
and they continue to innovate.
And they have consistently
stayed in lockstep
with us every time
we released a new OS,
every time there's
some new technology,
and every time there's
a new device to support.
Really impressive.
And we love this app because
it sets new benchmarks
for performance, for features,
for use of Apple technology,
for multi-device support,
and for accessibility.
And I'd like to ask Ryan
to show the app off now.
>> Hey. Thanks, John.
My name is Ryan Dour.
I'm an engineer on the
Accessibility Team here
at Apple, but I'm also a deejay.
All of my life, I've
been visually impaired.
But during high school
and college,
I lost most of my
remaining usable vision.
I've always deejayed with
CD players and mixers
because they offer a
hands-on tactile experience.
However, with the rise
of digital deejaying,
I was feeling pretty left out.
About a year ago, I got my
hands on djay Pro for the Mac
and this external deejay
controller and I got back
into it, and it's been
a great time since.
However, djay Pro for iPad
takes accessible deejaying
to a whole new level, and I'd
love to show it to you now.
So, over here, I have an
iPad Pro running djay Pro
and this external mixer.
I'm going to go ahead and
throw on my headphones now.
So, here's the thing
that's interesting.
The external deejay
controller acts
as an extension of
the onscreen UI.
And so I can use it
to really create kind
of a pretty cool performance.
Also, you're probably wondering
what of this can I see.
Not much. I pretty much can see
the light coming from the screen
and some of the, you know,
colorful lights coming
from the deejay controller,
but that's about it.
So knowing that, we're
going to use VoiceOver
to control this interface.
Let's go ahead and
get the music started.
OK, so the first thing
I'd like to point out is
that I have access
to information I've
never had before.
For example, the time.
How much time is
left on this track?
Let's find out.
That's perfect.
OK. So I'm the deejay, I'm
supposed to keep the music going
and now I have that
kind of information.
I also can use these
tempo sliders.
For example, if I touch it
right now -- hold on a second.
So we hear it's at a
standard playback speed.
But if I slow it down
using the deejay controller
and I touch it again,
we can hear exactly how far
I slowed that track down.
That's really cool.
I also can use these
multidimensional effects pads.
For example, if I touch
it the first time --
but the second time.
Really cool stuff, right?
So between these effects
pads, this external controller
and all this accessible UI,
I can do a pretty
cool performance.
So I'd like to go ahead
and ask the stage here
to please take VoiceOver
off of the PA systems --
that it's only available
to me and my headphones.
Cool. Thank you very much.
And I'm going to
mix for you now.
Here we go.
[ Music ]
[ Applause ]
So that's djay Pro
from Algoriddim.
[ Applause ]
>> Ryan, you're the man.
>> I've got to tell you --
this is an incredible
custom user interface.
They did not use UIKit
with this interface at all.
They didn't get any of their
accessibility for free.
Considering that,
their implementation
of our accessibility APIs is
nothing less than spectacular.
So I want to let everybody know,
and especially all the
visually-impaired deejays
out there, this app has
really enriched my life.
So I absolutely cannot
wait to see what the rest
of you developers
make accessible next!
Thank you so much, John!
>> Yeah. Good job.
[ Applause ]
Ryan, you're the man.
djay Pro -- a beautiful, fully
accessible, super sophisticated,
high-performance app
built for iOS and OS X.
Congratulations, guys.
So those are our
winners this year --
two great student apps
worthy of a Design Award,
and 10 other incredible apps.
10 apps that set the
standard for this coming year.
Each of these apps has
something very unique.
They entertain in a new way.
They allow you to
communicate in a new way.
They educate in a new way.
They solve real problems
in a clever or new way.
And they open doors for
people and enable people
to do things they
couldn't do before.
And all of them are
incredibly well-designed
and extremely well-executed
on all four of our platforms.
Now winners today get to
take home, as you've seen,
the Apple Design Award Trophy.
When you tap it,
it lights up just
like the cover of your laptop.
It's very cool.
Go check it out from one
of the winners later on.
So you get the coveted
Apple Design Award Trophy,
as well as a prize
package including one
of almost everything that
we make -- fully loaded.
[ Applause ]
And you get some
prominent featuring
on the App Store
beginning tonight.
[ Applause ]
All right, we wanted to wrap up
this day with this fun event.
It's always fun for me to do the
Design Awards, to be involved
with this, to know
so many of you
and to see your apps
come along and then some
of them to arrive on stage.
It's always fun to
give out these awards.
But before we wrap up tonight,
we just wanted to tell you
about something else that we've
been working on that's fun.
And it's a little bit apart
from the Design Awards
that we've given out so far, but
it's a great way to end our day.
And it does tie into
building something that's fun,
and unique, and compelling.
So to talk about that, I'd like
to invite Ben Wolstenholme,
Cofounder and CEO of Madefire, a
developer of iOS and TV OS apps,
to join me here on stage.
Ben?
[ Applause ]
Thanks, John.
Great to be here.
So Madefire is all
about storytelling --
and in particular, comics.
We love comics because they're
such a powerful storytelling
format.
People learn to read
through comics.
People escape into other
worlds through comics.
Most of all, comics are
words and pictures perfect
for the visual world
that we live in.
We've been working closely with
Apple on something that we'd
like to share with you tonight.
As you may have seen earlier,
Apple today launched new
app review guidelines.
They're very different
to the guidelines
that we're all used to, and
they're much more approachable.
And after speaking with Apple
about this new approach,
we collaborated to create --
[ Applause ]
Oh, yes! App Review
Guidelines, the Comic Book.
OK. Apple has put a lot of
thought into reorganizing
and simplifying the
guidelines into five sections.
And this gave us a great
opportunity to work
with different illustrators
and to develop five totally
different graphic styles.
Each section is a visual story.
And we really wanted
the visuals to react
with the serious content
of the guidelines.
It's created a pretty
wild outcome,
and something we hope
will engage people
around these important
topics even
if you think you know
the guidelines already.
It's pretty useful.
The comic book will be
available for download
from the developer's site,
alongside the searchable
text version.
But you will get to take home
your printed comic book tonight.
[ Applause ]
Oh, yes, hard to believe.
In a world of screens,
a big part of what we do
at Madefire is enable people
to turn their stories
into motion books.
As you can see, motion books
are a reading experience
with motion, sound, and depth.
And we're thrilled to be
working on a motion book version
of the app review guidelines.
Here's a sneak peek.
[ Music ]
So, look out for the App Review
Guidelines motion book coming
soon to an Apple
device near you.
And you can get your
printed comic here tonight.
I hope you enjoy the read.
Thanks.
[ Applause ]
Thanks, ben.
It's pretty fun.
A great way to end a
fun event with that.
So let's wrap up here right now.
Congratulations, first of
all, to all of you who've done
such incredible work over
the past months, years,
as you worked on these apps
that tonight won an award.
Hats off to you.
You've put in just an enormous
amount of work designing
and developing these apps,
and they've set a new standard
for the entire community.
And thanks to you all
here, as well as folks
who are watching online.
We've got lots of people
dialed in through the WWDC app
and through the online stream
that we've got from this event.
Thank you for joining us
from around the world.
We look forward to seeing
what you're going to create
in this coming year, what you're
going to create based on things
that maybe you saw this evening
that inspired you to move
to a new level with your app
and with your development
and with your design, and
inspired by the new things
that you heard today through the
sessions earlier on in this day.
So we'd like to close.
Just before we close, I'd
like to ask the winners
to come back on stage.
And while they're doing that,
I just want to say thank you,
and have a great
week and good night.
[ Applause ]