[ Music ]
>> I guess I'm on.
[ Applause ]
Thank you.
We're going to be moving the
attendee bash to my house
over in Berkley, it's a
lot more fun over there.
So welcome to Session
717, Beyond Dictation,
Enhanced Voice-Control for
macOS and Applications.
I'm Sal Saghoian, I'm
the Product Manager
for Automation Technologies
at Apple.
Today we're going to be
talking about the Mac,
macOS and what happens when you
combine the speech recognition
architecture in the macOS with
the native automation frameworks
that are available to you
to produce some really
incredible results.
Now when you're talking
about speech recognition
and dictation it's grouped
into four different categories.
The first dictation is
basically about transcription,
about you speaking something
that getting transcribed and put
into the current text field.
Enhanced dictation advances that
ability by adding the ability
to edit the text and to
navigate within a text field.
Advanced commands
include the ability
to control an application's
interface,
as well as perform
dictation tasks as well.
You can click buttons, tabs,
menus, those kinds of things.
And finally, user commands are
custom dictation commands you
create yourself to
perform the kind of things
that aren't a part of the
standard library of commands
that come with the computer.
So in macOS in the
latest version a lot
of things got moved
around, so what I'm going
to do is take a very short
couple minutes and review
where all these different
technologies live,
how to turn them on
and then we're going
to have some real fun.
So begin with we'll take
a look at basic dictation.
Now if you open up the System
Preferences app the controls
for speech and dictation
used to be in this window,
but instead of where they
were there is now the
Siri preference.
And if we open the Siri
preference you'll see
that there are no controls in
there for dictation and speech.
It's important to understand
that Siri and dictation
and speech are two
different technologies.
They have different
functions, different uses,
and different purposes.
So if we close this
and we go back
out to the main preference
window and we search
for the word dictation
in the search field
at the top right you'll see
that interestingly the keyboard
preference is now selected.
And if we open that you'll see a
new button added to the Tab bar
of that window at the end
and it's for dictation.
If we select that there are
the dictation controls now
in macOS are now within the
Keyboard System Preference pane.
There's a couple of radio
buttons there initially
for turning it off and on.
And when you turn on
dictation, basic dictation,
you'll see this sheet drop
down and it has two bits
of information that are
important to understand.
The first is that what you say
gets recorded by the computer
and sent to Apple servers
so that it's transcribed
and that text is then sent
back to your computer.
In addition, for accuracy they
send up the names and addresses
from your contacts list so
that they can better match some
of the phrases that
you're saying.
If those terms are
okay with you,
then you just click the
Enable Dictation button
and now dictation is on.
And you can dictate
into any text field
like a TextEdit document,
into a messages window,
into a mail message, and even
into a URL input
field for Safari.
You can use dictation
anywhere on the computer
where you have a text field.
And it's good for doing short
things, names, addresses,
some short phrases, it's
really good for that.
But it does have
some limitations
in that you do need an
active Internet connection
to connect to the servers.
And it's also not intended
for use with long dictations
like if you're doing a business
letter, it's not really designed
for that kind of thing.
You'll have to keep activating
the dictation command all the
time and there really are no
editing controls for dealing
with mistakes or
changes you want
to make to the dictated text.
Which brings us to
the next category,
which is enhanced dictation.
Not only can you
dictate into text fields,
but you could navigate between
the different text fields
of a window and edit the text
that you have there as well.
That was a pretty nice
little animation there,
did you like that?
So if we go back to our
Preferences window here,
below the On Off button
that we just turned off
and on is a checkbox called
Use Enhanced Dictation.
And when you select this
three things happen.
The first is it allows your
computer to be used offline.
You no longer have to --
require an Internet connection
to Apple servers.
All the transcription is done
locally on your computer.
In addition, you can
dictate continuously.
So you can sit there
over a 20 minute period
to dictate a letter and work
continuously with the computer
so that it will actually
grab what you say
and type it in for you.
And the third thing is that
the computer can now give you
live feedback.
It can give you an audio
sound or a visual cue
that it has heard you, that it
has recognized what you have
to say.
So we're going to turn
that on and then go back
out to the main Preferences
window.
Now to see what kind of commands
are available to us we're going
to go to the Accessibility
System Preference pane
and scroll down that
list on the left
and select the thing
that says Dictation.
Your preferences for using
dictation on the computer
in an enhanced mode are now
displayed here on the right.
You have an option to mute the
audio when you're dictating.
So if you have iTunes playing
and you started dictation
it automatically mutes it.
You can have it play
a confirmation sound,
which is usually like a
little [swish sound] just
to let you know that
it heard you.
You'll hear this being used when
I do some demos here for you.
And you can also
assign a key word
so that the computer will
not react to what you say
until it hears that
key word first
like computer what time is it.
So to see the commands that
you've now enabled we're going
to click the Dictation Commands
button and we get this sheet
that comes down and it
lists all the commands.
Commands are grouped into suites
and suites contain
one or more commands.
You can search through all the
available commands using the
search field at the top.
And when you have a command
selected you can turn it off
or on by selecting that
checkbox to the left of it.
And you can also see the
syntactical options available
to you on the right-hand side.
A lot of commands can be spoken
a variety of different ways
and all of those different
ways will trigger the command
to execute.
So let's look at the first suite
of commands, the
Selection Suite.
This suite is designed
to select text.
So you can select a word,
a paragraph, a sentence
and you'll notice that
there is even a command
for selecting a phrase.
The Navigation Suite
is for navigating
within your editing area.
So you can go to the end, go
to the beginning, go to the end
of the sentence that
kind of thing.
You can scroll up, scroll
down, move left, move right.
So it's really designed to
help you move around a window
between different fields and
scrolling the view plane.
There is a short editing suite
that contains the ability
to cut, copy, paste, as well
as perform some transformations
like capitalize,
lowercase, uppercase,
those kinds of things.
And you'll notice that there
is one special command there
called Replace.
So you can say replace
this phrase
with this phrase,
that's quite handy.
There's a small formatting suite
for doing things like bold,
italicized underline and
there is a small system suite
for stopping dictation and for
also displaying a floating HUD
that lists all of the commands.
So if you're in the
middle of a dictation
and you're not sure what
command is available,
you can say show Commands and
this little HUD will appear.
So together these make a
pretty comprehensive set
for doing some basic
good editing
of what you're dictating.
And to show you I
recorded a little video
of me doing it in pages.
So I just said something
it gets transcribed.
Replace Brazil with America.
Select power, capitalize that,
go to end, new line, new line,
the future of wind
power is amazing period.
So I dictated to the computer,
it transcribed what I said.
I said select -- wait
until you see me live.
So then I used the Replace
command, I selected Brazil,
changed it to America,
I capitalized something,
I navigated around.
So you get the idea that, you
know, this is very powerful.
Enhanced dictation
gives you many things.
It allows you to work
continuously offline
on your computer with no
interaction necessary.
It's giving you live feedback,
but it does have
some limitations
and I call it it's procedural.
It means that it's
like describing how
to make a peanut
butter sandwich.
You hold the jar with this
hand, you turn the top this way.
So you have to guide
the computer
through the process
of what you're doing.
You have to tell it to move to
the end, new line, new line.
And that can take some
getting used to in order
to be able to do that smoothly.
The next category of recognition
is advanced commands and that's
where you augment the dictation
abilities with the ability
to control the application
interface.
So not only are you
being able to dictate,
but you can push buttons.
So if we go back to
this accessibility sheet
that we were looking at down
at the bottom is a checkbox
called Enable Advanced Commands.
And if you select that it turns
on new suites and expands some
of the suites of commands
that are available.
So the Navigation Suite now
expands to include things
for controlling the
application interface.
You can say show numbers
and a number will be placed
over every control
in the application
and then you can just speak
the number and that button
or menu will be pressed
and activated.
The System Suite is now
expanded to include the ability
to search spotlight and
that is really useful.
You can also show commands
and hide commands just
the same way as before.
There is now an Application
Suite for switching
between applications, for
quitting an application,
and hiding an application.
And there's a small Document
Suite that lets you open,
create, save, close documents
within an application.
So in addition to this existing
set of commands that we have,
the new set augments
that and expands some
of the key things there.
So let me show you how
that works when you use it.
And in this case
I'm going to use it
to create a document in Keynote.
So switch to Keynote and Keynote
will come forward, Show Commands
and you'll get that
floating HUD that has a list
of all the commands
that are available.
And if we look at the
document section there,
there's a command for new item.
And this is same thing as going
Command End on the keyboard
or selecting New
from the File menu.
So I'll say New Item, it
recognizes and since we're
in Keynote it brings
up the Template Picker
so I can pick what kind of
presentation I want to make.
I'm looking to make
a wide presentation
and at the top is a
button that I would click
if I was doing this by hand
to see the wide presentation
templates.
So I'll click Wide and that
will press the button for me
and reveal all the
wide presentations.
Now I'm looking for parchment,
so it doesn't appear
in this view.
So I'll have it scroll the
window by saying Scroll Down
and then there's
parchment at the very end.
And I can select that by
saying Click Parchment.
And once I do it will open
up a new Keynote document
with the parchment theme.
So you can see that advanced
commands augment dictation
by giving you control of
the application interface.
All the buttons and
tabs are available.
But again, like the
other categories
of speech recognition
there are some limitations
and it too is procedural.
You notice I had to
walk through each step
of doing the things required
to create a Keynote document.
I'm basically using my voice
as a mouse or a keyboard
and not all applications have
complete accessibility support.
Generally, they do
have good support,
but that could also be an issue.
You might not be able to
give a command for the thing
that you want it to do.
But here's the good
news user commands.
This is where we leave the
world of accessibility behind.
This is where the power of
automation and the power
of speech recognition
fuse together
to produce incredible tools.
So let me show you how you
access these on the computer.
So in this window is a
secret button for turning
on this power ability and it
is right here, this + button.
It doesn't look like much, it
looks like any other + button,
but when you press that + button
a new suite is added called User
Commands and by default a new
blank command is set up for you.
So now we can create our own
command and to do that I'm going
to describe some parameters on
the left-hand side beginning
with what is the phrase that
I want to use as a command.
So let's say I want to create
a command to tell the computer
to take my picture right.
So I enter take my
picture in there.
So when I say the words take my
picture the computer will do the
actions I want it to do.
Now you can determine if this
command is always available
or only within a
specific application
by selecting it from
this pop-up.
I'm going to leave it
set for Any Application.
And to perform the action you
have a menu of possible things
that the computer will do for
you upon dictating that command.
You can have the computer
open up certain finder items
like certain documents
that you want opened.
You can have the computer
open a specific URL.
You can have it paste
text that you've liked
like your favorite
legalese statement.
You can have it paste data like
your favorite corporate logo.
You can have it press
a keyboard shortcut.
You can have it select any
menu in any application
and you can even have it
run an Automator workflow
or AppleScript or
JavaScript script.
And as a matter fact
the OS ships
with nine pre-done
Automator workflows for you.
The first three here are
for starting a recording
in the QuickTime player.
You can say new audio recording,
new screen recording,
new video recording.
There is one for going to
the Apple website of course
and there are five for
navigating within iTunes.
So you can say show me
the top family movies
and it will go right
to that page
within the iTunes application.
And at the bottom is
a choice for other
that will let you pick
your own Automator workflow
or own JavaScript or
AppleScript script and make
that the action that gets run.
But you'll notice there is
one for take my picture,
so I'm going to select that
and click the Done button
to create this command.
And it automatically gets
added to the list of commands.
So my user suite now has one
command called take my picture
and this is what it looks
like when you run it.
So I start dictation, I go
take my picture, it recognizes,
brings up the camera picker, I
smile and it takes my picture
and puts it in photos
for me automatically.
So user commands are different
than the other types of commands
because they're task oriented.
They're not so much procedural
where you're telling it
to do this, then
this, then this.
You're basically
giving a command
to execute this particular task
no matter how many steps it
takes, no matter
what it needs to do.
And it really does expose
all the power of automation
that is available to you
on the operating system.
And you still get all the
other dictation abilities
that you currently have
with the other ones.
It's hands-free, always
on, visual feedback,
you don't need a net connect.
It is incredibly powerful,
but as you saw how
many steps it took me
to make a user dictation command
if I wanted to make a hundred
of those to really do
something with a particular app,
it might be a little
bit cumbersome
to create that until today.
Today, there's a set of
custom dictation commands
that I'm going to give you today
that will let you control
the Finder iWork and Photos
and some of the other apps.
And they take advantage
of this automation
and speech recognition
technology together.
So let me switch over here and
we'll watch these in action.
Okay, so I'm getting over a
cold my voice is a bit lower,
so we'll see if she even
pays attention to me today.
And I have a mic set
up here because we're
in this huge boomy
[phonetic] room.
But let me tell you
when I'm in the office
at Apple I just use the computer
it's open there connected
to my monitor and I can talk to
this thing from across the room
and it works perfectly.
So I'm going to be using
this today and I expect one
or two errors, but
let's see what happens.
So let's try that thing
about creating a new
presentation in Keynote.
Switch to Keynote, make
a new presentation okay.
How about let's make
a different one.
Make a wide presentation,
oh okay.
How about one with a
particular template.
Make a new wide presentation
using the gradient template.
Oh that's pretty good,
let's try a different theme.
Make a new standard presentation
with the brush canvas theme.
Pretty good.
Close all without saving.
So the whole idea of
having to be procedural
to create a document
you saw me go
through all the steps
is now like no.
I'm thinking about what I need
to do, give me a new document
with this template, this
width I'm done, I'm there.
So that's good for
creating a new document,
let's see how you can work
with an existing document.
So let me pull up a document
that I have on the computer
and let's work with
it a little bit.
Search spotlight for
presentation the States
of the United States,
open result.
She's chugging today.
Start at the top.
[ Music ]
Oh I'm good with slides,
I'm good with slides.
[ Music ]
Next slide.
Go to slide nine.
Read the presenter notes.
>> California's diverse
geography ranges
from the Sierra Nevada in
the east to the Pacific Coast
in the west and from the
redwood forests of the northwest
to the Mohave Desert
areas in the southeast.
>> Tell me about this image.
>> Although Death Valley is a
below sea level basin a great
diversity of life flourishes
in this land of extremes.
>> Take a break.
Take a break.
Export the presenter
notes to mail.
Export presenter notes to mail.
That's pretty handy I could
use that a couple times.
Switch to Keynote.
Show related items.
So we have a spotlight window
down here with all the items
that are related to this.
There's a GarageBand file with
the shaker song in it okay.
There's even the email
that I just sent.
There's a bunch of
images that I used.
There's a picture
of the US flag.
There's also an audio
recording that I put in right,
that was the audio
recording and some links.
So it was really easy for me
to find things that are related
to the document that I'm working
on just by asking for them.
Close this without saving.
So you can see this concept
of having task oriented
things is really useful
because it doesn't really
interfere with the mental flow
that you have going, especially
when you're creating something.
So let me use user commands
and dictation commands
to create some content.
So we've seen it open a
document, create a new document
and we've seen it
work with a document.
Let me actually create some
content using these commands.
Switch to photos.
These are some photos I took on
my trip down the Rhone River.
I took one of those
Viking type cruises.
Lots of fun I highly
recommend that.
Select all photos.
Help me to add titles.
>> Enter the title
for image one of five.
>> You know, normally doing this
kind of thing is a real pain
because you've got to get down
there in the interface and look
at these little things.
And, you know, being able
to have this guide you
through something sometimes
is just the easiest way
to do something.
On the Rhone River yeah,
you need that special
character there.
Rhone River.
>> Five of five.
>> This was an incredible
Roman temple right
in the middle of town.
>> Done.
>> So using that command I was
able to add titles to a bunch
of images really quickly.
Select all photos, make a
new presentation with these.
Okay, so it just did [applause].
Yeah, I mean that's
a pain right,
who wants to do the 40 steps
that it takes to do that.
I can think of it why can't I
just ask the computer do it,
obviously it can right.
Go to slide one.
Change master slide
to title center.
Scratch that.
Change master slide
to title center.
And let's see vacation photos.
Select Photos, capitalize
that, stop, edit.
Okay, let's see what
I've got here.
Move the slide to the end.
Okay.
>> Done.
>> And then I want this
to go down around there.
I think no, the lock came
first and then that okay.
This needs some tweaking,
this is bad.
Edit this in photos.
So the computer knows where
that photo came from doesn't it.
Why should I have to go spend my
time doing that kind of thing?
Let's set it to crop and I'll
straighten this out a little bit
and then as long as I'm adding
I'm going to crop it to get rid
of the guy standing there
and make this a little bit
more interesting, more focused
on the lock rather than the
rest of the stuff around it.
And Photos has some
nice little tools
for doing that, so
that looks good.
Show this in Keynote.
It knows where it
is in Keynote right.
Let me select it,
update this image.
Update this image.
So I don't have to go
through that whole process
about doing stuff
I'm just thinking,
I'm creating here
on the fly right.
Let's make his little bit bigger
so that it looks a little
bit more interesting.
And then -- oh this is
great, the Popes' Palace,
it's really interesting.
Show this in Maps.
So here it is in Maps and
let's use the nice 3-D feature
of Apple Maps.
And let's see if we can get a
nice background for that photo
to show people the context and
the fact that the thing's right
in the middle of this
old Roman part of town.
You can see the circular
area that was
like the original
village there right.
Okay, export this
map to Keynote.
All right, very good
and let's kind
of crop this in here
a little bit.
There we go.
I haven't done the command
yet for crop the slide.
It's a good idea though.
Let's go paste it and
put it to the back here.
I'm going to copy this and
put this on top of this,
it's like a little trick right.
So that I can do like a
magic move and then reveal.
So I need to apply a magic move.
Apply magic move.
Apply a dissolve.
Do that again.
Okay, so I got the transitions
and then oh, Pont du Gard.
Okay, this one we need
to fix a little bit.
Scale this to fit slide width.
All right, that's good.
And make a long panoramic
sequence.
>> Done.
>> Okay and while we're
at it put descriptions
on top of every image.
That could take a while to do.
And so after this trip I was so
impressed with these locations
that I went on the
Internet, I did some research
as to how many people visit
these sites every year.
And I have a spreadsheet
that has that information.
Search spotlight for
spreadsheet tourism in France.
Open result.
Select the table.
Export this table to
Keynote as a chart.
Good, that could be handy.
And let's scale this
down a little bit
so that it fits there nice.
Okay, start from the top.
All right, so this was a Roman
temple right in the middle
of town, it's been
around forever.
They actually turned it into
a movie theater for a while.
And this was us going through
a lock on the Rhone River,
there's about four or five
locks during the course of that.
This is the power
station that they use
to provide power for Arles.
And this is Pont du Gard,
which is this incredible
Roman aqueduct
that was built like
3,000 years ago.
And the fact that this huge
thing that's three stories tall
it's still here today and
still in the condition it's
in is absolutely amazing.
It spans this entire long valley
and I'll bet if we try to do
that today it would run in
the billions of dollars.
But it's quite impressive.
And that's Pont du Gard.
And of course, there
is the Popes' Palace
and it's located right in the
center of the old Roman town
like you can see here.
And people find these
sites really interesting,
there's millions and
millions means of people
that visit these every year.
Save this presentation.
And as a matter fact, why
don't I while I'm at it,
but I don't have
a free port here.
Let's see if I can copy
this to my thumb drive.
So I'm going to stick
a thumb drive in here.
Save this presentation to
my thumb drive and eject it.
Scratch that.
Save this presentation to
my thumb drive and eject it.
>> Saving document
vacation photos
to drive digital briefcase.
Dismounting digital briefcase.
>> So this is the kind of thing
that you can do where, you know,
you're still in the
application you don't have
to leave what you're doing
to dismount something,
to eject something,
to copy something.
>> Done.
>> That deals something
with the Finder.
I mean you just tell
the computer to do it.
It knows how to do
this stuff right.
Why shouldn't we just be
able to tell it to do that?
So where do you get this stuff?
Add a blank slide.
Turn this into a QR code.
Scale down 10%.
There we go.
So all of this material is
available for to you today
and I'm going to show
you where to get it.
So let's go back to the slides
here and my slide advancer.
So what are these type
of commands useful for?
Well we saw that they're really
good for when you want to remain
in context and you want actions
and tasks performed for you.
They are really good for
performing multistep tasks
and like when I had to
go through and name all
of those images, so that I could
use their descriptions later.
They're also good for tasks
that require dexterity.
Can you imagine copying the
description from an image file
on a slide and then creating a
text box, placing it just so on
that and doing that for
an entire presentation?
Boy, you have to be a wizard
to be able to do that quickly.
But with voice command,
with a dictation command that's
just asking that be done.
You can also move data.
So like I had the map in Maps,
I wanted it over in Keynote.
So voice commands and dictation
commands are perfect for that
and excellent for
data transformation.
So I had a table with data that
I wanted as a chart in Keynote
and I was able to give it a
command and have that executed.
You can perform tasks
that aren't available
in the application
UI that you're in.
For example, turn
this into a QR code.
That's a perfect example of
something you'd want to do
in a presentation, but
it's just not there.
And things that the user wants
to do, but doesn't know how.
Man, all the people in
my family do not know how
to use the Clipboard, do not
know how to do a screen capture,
do not know how to use AirDrop.
So being able to do that with
a spoken dictation command
is perfect.
So what are they good for?
Dictation commands are good for
solving all of these problems
and for being a solution.
So how does it work?
Well, I only have a couple
minutes so I'm going to kind
of boot out of that for a second
and jump past that section.
It's basically magic and
I'm going to kick back in
and tell you where to go
to get these resources.
Everything you need to
know about how they work
and the collection I just
showed you is available for you
on dictationcommands.com.
So to summarize, the power
of speech recognition
and automation working
together makes it
so that dictation is no
longer just another way
to enter text into a text field.
And speech is no longer just
an assistive technology.
And now voice is a peer
to touch, keys and cursor.
You can use your
voice the same way
that you use the other
inputs into the computer.
And this is what's possible
when you have macOS and all
of these technologies
working together.
It's only something that
can happen on a Mac.
So thank you so much for
being part of my day.
Thank you for being here.
Thank you for being part of
this session I appreciate it.
[ Applause ]